<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine aduertisements for the good of the church and common-wealth well worthy the serious consideration of the most honourable High Court of Parliament late assembled, and hereafter to be assembled againe.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 199 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10404</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101634</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837443</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837443</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1764</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00286)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1764)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1235:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine aduertisements for the good of the church and common-wealth well worthy the serious consideration of the most honourable High Court of Parliament late assembled, and hereafter to be assembled againe.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 80 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the successors of G. Thorp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name supplied and publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Usually bound with: An humble petition to the Kings most excellent majestie: Amsterdam, 1625 (STC 14425).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James I, 1603-1625.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1764:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1764:1"/>
            <p>CERTAINE ADVERTISEMENTS FOR THE GOOD OF THE <hi>CHVRCH AND COMMON-WEALTH,</hi> WELL WORTHY THE SERIOVS conſideration of the moſt Honourable High <hi>Court of Parliament late aſſembled, and</hi> hereafter to be aſſembled <hi>againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZRA 7.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Whatſoeuer is commanded by the God of Heauen, let it be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently done for the Houſe of the God of Heauen: For why ſhould there be wrath againſt the Realme of the King, and his Sonnes?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME 119.46.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will ſpeake of thy Teſtimonies before Kings, and will not be aſhamed.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1764:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1764:2"/>
            <head>CERTAINE ADVERTISEMENTS FOR THE GOOD OF THE CHVRCH and Common wealth, well worthy the ſerious conſideration of the moſt Honourable <hi>High Court of Parliament late aſſembled</hi> and hereafter to be aſſembled <hi>againe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, and moſt renowmed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies of the Lord,and of the Lords Annointed (our gracious and dread Soueraigne King <hi>James</hi>) I am the bolder to preſent theſe my few Obſeruations following to your moſt Honourable and Chriſtian conſideration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his moſt excellent Maieſtie in his late gracious Speech vnto you in your Vpper Houſe on <hi>March</hi> the ſix &amp; twentieth laſt paſt, hath plainely in Princely and Chriſtian manner teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, the publike good of this his Kingdome to be ſo precious vnto him, that no priuate perſon whatſoeuer (were he neuer ſo deare vnto him) ſhould be ſo reſpected by him by many degrees, as the publike good, not onely of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, but euen of any particular Corporation that is a Member of it. For by this his moſt Princely care of the Common wealth, we cannot but in all dutie aſſure our ſelues of his like moſt Chriſtian regard of, and affection vnto the Church of God: both generally within theſe his Maieſties Dominions, and alſo as the ſame is particularly diſtributed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to particular Congregations in euerie Shiere, and Citie, and Towne. And as his Maieſtie in his ſaid Speech ſpeaketh of the gouernement of the Common wealth by compariſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with his Coppices, ſo if it ſhall pleaſe him to take a vew
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1764:3"/>of the Churches, wherein ſome haue perſwaded him <hi>eſſe om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia bene,</hi> I doubt not, but that he ſhall finde the ſame in the like ſtate that he found his Coppices, and by his Coppices the Common wealth. As therefore by your helpe he hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued further light then before he had, touching the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Common wealth, ſo I doe humbly craue your moſt Honourable and Chriſtian ayd for his Royall informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſtate and corruptions of the Church with their cauſes, that here I preſent to your moſt Chriſtian Senate, and by other that your own Chriſtian wiſedomes can better ſhew then any one ſo ſimple as I am.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> May it therefore pleaſe your Honourable Court to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">The free paſſage of the Goſpel.</note> firſt and principally the free paſſage and preaching of the Goſpel without ſuch heauie burthens as for a long time haue beene impoſed vpon the Miniſters thereof; the which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding may as well be ſpared without preiudice to any ſaue onely to the Epiſcopall Courts, as the paring of a mans nayles.<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33 Mat. 22.38 Luke 1.75 Tit. 2.12 1 Tim. 2.2</note> We are commanded, <hi>firſt to ſeeke the Kingdome of God.</hi> And the firſt and the great Commandement is the loue of God. There can be no righteouſneſſe towards man, without holineſſe and godlineſſe towards God: and both theſe are the grounds of a quiet and peaceable life. This one thing is needfull:<note place="margin">Luk. 10.41</note> the which he that chooſeth, chooſeth the good part, which ſhall not be taken away.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Secondly, That the Miniſters ſilenced by reaſon of the before intimated vnneceſſarie burdens,<note place="margin">Ministers ſilenced to be well conſidered.</note> be well conſidered, in reſpect of the innocencie, and integritie of their life in all things: the matters of ſubſcription and conformitie only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted: as alſo in reſpect of their great paines and diligence in their Miniſterie: and of the fruites thereof apparant vnto all men in their ſeuerall charges. They haue beene indeed and daily are charged with diſloyaltie,<note place="margin">Ezra 4.15 Eſter 3.8 Acts 24.16</note> as the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſometimes were: yet they may truly with <hi>Paul</hi> ſay they <hi>endeauour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to haue a cleare conſcience towards God and towards men.</hi> And all that they doe in not ſubſcribing and conforming they doe onely of conſcience towards God, and may therefore vſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1764:3"/>the ſame proteſtation that the <hi>Reubenites, Gadites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſh. 22.22</note> and halfe Tribe of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> vſed: yea they haue alſo manifeſted the ſame and made it fully knowne by their Doctrine,<note place="margin">2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10</note> manner of liuing, purpoſe, faith, long ſuffering, patience, perſecution (by the Prelates) and other afflictions. Some likewiſe being as well borne, as moſt of their Aduerſaries, and hauing in their youth refuſed great Temporalties offered, if they would haue diuerted their Studies to the Law, haue now ſubmitted themſelues to want and pouertie in their age, when they haue moſt need of plentie. And in all that they doe in the promiſes, they plead conſcience farre otherwiſe then Papiſts that haue alwaies ſhewed themſelues moſt rebellious and traiterous.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thoſe that are contumeliouſly called Puritans are the beſt Proteſtants,<note place="margin">Puritans the beſt Proteſtants</note> in reſpect of the greater oppoſition betwixt them and their aſſertions, and betwixt the Papiſts and their aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and alſo of the greater hatred of Papiſts againſt them, then againſt the common Proteſtants. And as for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſilenced for not ſubſcribing and conforming; they are as good Subiects as any his Maieſtie hath: yea they doe not ſubſcribe and conforme, euen in loyaltie and of conſcience towards his Maieſtie: as alſo in feare of Gods diſpleaſure as well againſt his Maieſtie, as againſt themſelues; the ſinnes of Subiects prouoking Gods diſpleaſure againſt Princes as well as againſt themſelues: as it is plentifully ſhewed by Doctor <hi>Hall</hi> in his Sermon vpon <hi>1 Sam. 12.24, 25.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.14, 15, 24, 25. Prou. 28.2 Iſa 3.1</note> preached on the <hi>24</hi> of <hi>March, 1613.</hi> The ſame is alſo further euident by other Scriptures, as likewiſe by many examples of diuers that in matters apparantly of no great moment hauing conformed themſelues to the commandement of their Princes haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked the Lords wrath againſt ſuch Princes themſelues. To omit that of <hi>Doeg,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.18. 2 Chro. 24 21. 2 Sam. 11.15.</note> and that of ſome to <hi>Ioaſh</hi> (as being in deed in great matters) worthy of moſt due conſideration, is both the firſt obedience of <hi>Ioah</hi> againſt <hi>Vriah</hi> before he knew the reaſon of <hi>Dauids</hi> commandement, in reſpect of the manifold euill conſequences thereof: and alſo his ſecond obedience af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1764:4"/>in numbring of the people,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 24</note> in reſpect of the great Plague that followed.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiections </seg>5</label> If the ſmalneſſe of the things impoſed be obiected, Firſt, This is but a meere <hi>petitio principi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.23</note> it hauing beene often plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully proued otherwiſe. Secondly, As ſmall duties are as well to be performed as great, ſo ſmall ſinnes are as well to be refrained as great: the rather becauſe as God bleſſed with good ſucceſſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> in not bowing to <hi>Haman</hi> vpon the Kings command,<note place="margin">Eſt. 3.3, 4</note> the doing whereof ſeemeth a ſmall matter, and ſuch as might haue admitted a good excuſe, ſo he dealt ſeuerely with <hi>Vzza</hi> for an act in ſhew of ſmall account.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 6.4</note> It is ſometime better loyaltie not to yeald then to yeald obedience to the command of Princes, though good and religious: as appeareth by the example of <hi>Ioah</hi> before mentioned,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3</note> and by them that would not ſuffer <hi>Dauid</hi> to goe out with them to battell againſt <hi>Abſolom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 21.17</note> and by the anſwer of other vnto him after a great danger: Eſpecially by them that would not obey <hi>Saul</hi>'s commandement for putting <hi>Ionathan</hi> to death,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.44.</note> euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Saul</hi> had euer bewraied ſo great wickedneſſe as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he did,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.17.</note> as well as they that afterward refuſed his like command for killing the Lords Prieſts. If any ſhall obiect ſuch examples to diſgrace our Chriſtian King, as making him like to <hi>Saul:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodor. Hiſt. Eccl. L. 2. C. 16.</note> he may well be anſwered, as <hi>Liberius</hi> ſometime a good Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (now the Seat of <hi>Antichrist</hi>) anſwered a flattering Courtier <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that charged the ſaid <hi>Liberius</hi> for alleadging the example of the three Children in <hi>Daniel</hi> to purge himſelfe of ſingularitie in defending boldly <hi>Athan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſius</hi> againſt the Emperour <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and many Biſhops, that he compared the ſaid Emperour to <hi>Nebuchadnezzer:</hi> No ſaid <hi>Liberius:</hi> But thou without reaſon doſt condemne a man that hath not beene brought into Iudgement. Euen ſo (I ſay) may all ſuch Flatterers and pickthankes be anſwered, that ſnatch at euerie aduantage againſt ſuch as plead for the Innocent, whereby to bring them into diſpleaſure with their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes: Neither alſo can it be iuſtly charged to be ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſpoken to the encouragement of other (Papiſts or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1764:4"/>Atheiſts) not to obey iuſt and lawfull commands: Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as by many Bookes, to ſubſcribe and conforme are ſhewed not to be lawfull by diuers arguments not anſwered, nor anſwerable: and alſo becauſe the parties not ſubſcribing and conforming doe in all other things ſhew all alleageance, and teach all other ſo to doe whereas the contrarie is daily ſeene in Papiſts and Atheiſts as they dare, and haue any op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie and meanes according to their mindes. Do not alſo the parties pleaded for ſubmit themſelues to ſuffer any thing for their not ſubſcribing and conforming? That of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel, Obedience is better then ſacrifice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> is ſpoken of obedience to God, and not of obedience vnto men, as the Text plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſheweth; and it being ſayd to the king himſelfe, euen to <hi>Saul,</hi> for his tranſgreſſing the expreſſe commandement of God, and not for tranſgreſſing any commandement of man. For he being the king was not ſubiect to any man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The premiſes are the more to be reſpected in regard of the tenderneſſe of conſcience,<note place="margin">The tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> apparant by <hi>Dauids</hi> heart ſmiting him for cutting only of a Lap of <hi>Saul's</hi> garment: and by the great griefe of <hi>Iohn Hus</hi> in remembrance of his fineneſſe in apparell whiles he was young, and of his playing at <hi>Cheſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24 6 Acts and Mon. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1596. p. 580. Gen. 42.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and alſo by the accuſation of the conſciences of the brethren of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> for things done againſt <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> long after the doing of them. (Oh that the Prelats would ſeriouſly conſider this in time towards their brethren:) yea, alſo becauſe to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the conſcience (being well conſidered) is worſe then the demand of <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> for thruſting out all the right eyes of the Inhabitants of <hi>Iabeſh Gilead.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.2</note> For if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be wounded, the whole mind is blinded: And if Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters be blinde, how ſhall they giue light to their people: <hi>If the light that is in them be darkeneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>how great is their darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi> And if Miniſters be ſo wounded in their conſciences that themſelues haue no comfort;<note place="margin">Pro. 18.14.</note> 
               <hi>(for a wounded ſpirit who can beare?)</hi> how can they comfort other? Oh that his excellent Maieſtie in the Spirit of the Lord would be pleaſed and moued to relieue ſuch Miniſters vpon conſideration
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1764:5"/>hereof, as <hi>Saul</hi> in the ſame ſpirit was moued to relieue <hi>Iabeſh Gilead.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 11.6</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That fayling ſometime in greater matters is not ſufficient to proue ſmaller things not to be refrained of conſcience,<note place="margin">A good conſcience may fayle in greater matters and yet ſtick at ſmall.</note> appeareth by <hi>David,</hi> who notwithſtanding he were in his minde troubled for that ſmall matter before mentioned, yet afterward many wayes ſinned moſt grieuouſly againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> both in his adulterie and alſo afterward. The greater alſo and heauier the burden of other ſinnes is, the more ſuch as ſo feele the ſame haue neede to take heed of increaſing their burden by any other thing:<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.22.</note> yea, <hi>to abſtaine from all appearance of euill.</hi> They alſo that do obiect the former do moſt offend in greater matters themſelues: as againſt Gods Word, ſo alſo againſt the Lawes of the Land: vſing all meanes daily to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the proceeding of the Law againſt themſelues: and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the benefit of the Law vnto others: thereby bewraying that themſelues would rule and raigne as Lords and Kings, ſubiect to no Law, and ſeeking to haue all other ſubiect to themſelues: like to that king that <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaid ſhould do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his owne will.<note place="margin">Dan. 11.36.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Neyther alſo do the Miniſters moleſted, plead conſcience in reſpect of themſelues only,<note place="margin">Miniſters refraine conformitie in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Rulers.</note> but alſo in reſpect of their Rulers, and moleſters, and that becauſe to moleſt ſuch is a thing more dangerous, then to be moleſted. In ſuch things it is worſe to be agents then patients: Though <hi>Dauid</hi> at the firſt would not be diſſwaded from numbring the people, yet how wofully and dolefully afterward did he cry out, as a child beaten laying it wholly vpon himſelfe,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.10.17.</note> without impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation thereof to any other: Oh that ſuch Rulers of their brethren would not be deceiued herein. That which ſeemeth now a ſmall thing, may herafter be great and heauie. A Gnat is but a ſmall thing: a flea leſſe: yet eyther of both doth trouble the greateſt as well as the leaſt; the higheſt as well as the loweſt. Great perſons haue great meanes for ſolacing themſelues; but alas who (as I ſayd before) <hi>can beare a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirit?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18.14.</note> ſpirit?</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1764:5"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> I doe further in all humilitie beſeech your moſt Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Senate,<note place="margin">The inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of Miniſters to be tryed euen by the Lawes of the Land.</note> that the innocencie of the Miniſters before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned may be tryed, not only by the Word of God; but alſo by the Lawes of the Land: and that the learned Iudges and other Lawyers may freely and at large argue their cauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Maieſtie and your Honorable Court, being by an oath of the Lord firſt charged vpon their alleageance, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, plainly, and fully to deliuer their iudgements touching the Lawes of the Land in that behalfe: as alſo by his excellent Maieſtie being enboldned ſo to ſpeake without feare of any danger to themſelues by ſuch ſpeaking, eyther for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or for the time to come.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> If his Maieſties Prerogatiue Royall ſhall be obiected for iuſtifying of all his Officers in their proceedings againſt ſuch Miniſters, may it pleaſe his Maieſtie to conſider,<note place="margin">The Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue Royall.</note> not only what he may do by humane Iuſtice as he is a Prince, but alſo what he may doe and muſt do by the Word of the King of Kings, and as himſelfe is ſubiect to that Word, and is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and in Chriſt a ſpirituall King, and heyre of a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome euerlaſting in Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: thereby hauing greater priuiledges and prerogatiues, then as according to fleſh and blood, hee is Royally deſcended, and an earthly King of many Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions: This I could largely demonſtrate, but that I would alſo haue other matters to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> The indignities done to the foreſayd Miniſters are great and greiuous. Firſt, their often callings to diuers Courts,<note place="margin">The indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities done to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> as well farre of as neere at hand: at all tymes and ſeaſons of the yeare: whether they be young or old, ſtrong or weake, of good abilitie to beare the charges of ſuch iournies, or poore and in want: Secondly, the reſtreynt of their miniſterie; Thirdly, Depriuation of their liuings in their old age, when they haue moſt need of maintenance: hauing eſpecially liued plentifully all their dayes before: and then alſo hauing greater charges: and hauing before beene diſtributers to other, then forced with griefe of heart to take reliefe of other: hauing before giuen the Bread of Life to other: and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1764:6"/>in old age wanting themſelues bread for this life: and not being able to giue their children ſuch education as whereby to fit them for Church or Common wealth: neyther ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing wherewith to preferre their children in mariage: how well ſoeuer borne, educated, or qualified. A thing whereby the miſerable ſtate of the Iſraelites is ſometyme amplified. <hi>viz.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.63 Iob 30.26.31. Pſa. 137.2.</note> that their maides were not giuen in mariage. By all which they that before haue beene meanes to make many glad, are now themſelues <hi>made to weepe, and</hi> (as it were) <hi>to hang vp their harps, &amp;c. and euen when they looked for good, then to haue euill come vpon them: and when they looked for light, then to haue darkeneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 8.15. and 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>and when they looked for peace, then to haue no good: and for a tyme of health, then to haue trouble.</hi> Hereto alſo may be referred the dolefull complaint of Ieruſalem, <hi>My Prieſts and my Elders periſhed in the citie, whiles they ſought for meat to refreſh their ſoules.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 1.19.</note> Is not this the more, becauſe it is not by any ſiege of foreine enimies, but by the rigour of them that profeſſe themſelues freinds, pillers, and chiefe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of the Church?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> To the premiſes may be added, that, that which the dead gaue vnto ſuch Miniſters in their godly deuotion, hath beene reſtreyned from them by their aduerſaries, contrary to that of <hi>Tullie</hi> againſt <hi>Antonie Philippi</hi> the 2. and of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpianus</hi> a Ciuill Lawyer in his deſcription of a Teſtament Tit. 20. So are ſuch Miniſters made more vile then notorious malefactors in common gaoles, that without any contradiction enioy what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is giuen vnto them by the laſt Will and Teſtament of any deceaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> By the foreſayd indignities againſt ſuch Miniſters, and by ſupply of their places with men eyther altogether vnſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,<note place="margin">The effects of indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties done to Miniſters.</note> or nothing ſo ſufficient as they that were depriued, God himſelfe is ſhortened of many excellent duties before performed in ſuch places, and highly diſhonored by many great ſinnes and outrages before reſtreyned: and that publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and on thoſe dayes that ſhould be moſt religiouſly ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, no man ſaying to any that do ſo diſhonor the Lord, why do ye ſo?</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1764:6"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> If his Maieſtie be informed that the Miniſters before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned are now as plentifully prouided for,<note place="margin">His Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie falſly informed of ſilenced Ministers ſufficient mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</note> as when they enioyed their places, this might be eaſily and plentifully anſwered if this place permitted the ſame; and too lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table experience teacheth the contrarie. Howſoeuer alſo at the firſt ſome perhaps were ſomewhat regarded, yet as light burdens farre caryed are heauie; ſo by that charge long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued men are wearied. Are not diuers alſo gathered to their fathers, that whiles they liued were bountifull? Are not alſo the ſtates of men changeable, and their mindes mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table? And what comfort is in ſuch vncerteynties? Laſtly this obiection ſeemeth to be of ſuch as neuer thinke any thing enough for themſelues, but euery thing too much for other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Beſides all the premiſes, the foreſayd Miniſters are greatly iniuryed in their names, <hi>which are better then great riches,<note place="margin">Ministers wronged in their names.</note> &amp;c.</hi> and that not only by moſt reprochefull and contumelious words caſt vpon them euery where priuatly and in Epiſcopall Courts publikely, but alſo by moſt falſe, wicked, and vniuſt termes in their ſentences of ſuſpenſion, excommunication,<note place="margin">Prou. 22.1. Eccleſ. 7.2</note> depriuation, and degradation remayning vpon publike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord for all poſteritie, and to the great preiudice of the poſteritie of ſuch Miniſters: the rather becauſe ſuch ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are begun after the Romane, and Papall manner, <hi>In Dei nomine, Amen.</hi> And this indignitie touching the names of ſuch Miniſters, is yet the greater, becauſe of the diſgracefull termes giuen vnto them in the preface to the new tranſlation of the Engliſh Bibles prefixed before the ſayd Bibles, and therefore to be read by euerie one that hath or ſhall haue the ſaid Bibles: by all the which meanes, all other doe the more contumeliouſly vſe them, Swaggerers, Blaſphemers, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of the Word, Drunkards, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
               <note place="margin">None go in more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note>Moreouer, none go in more perſonall danger of bodily hurt then ſuch Miniſters. No not the moſt vile perſons that are, becauſe all ſee authoritie ſo bent againſt them: yea more againſt ſuch, then againſt Recuſant Papiſts, Blaſphemers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1764:7"/>Drunkards,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.31. Lam. 4.9.</note> &amp;c. So that ſuch Miniſters may truly ſay, <hi>They dye daily:</hi> as alſo complaine with the Prophet that <hi>they that are ſlaine by the Sword, are better then they, that dye ſo daily,</hi> and by ſo many meanes. Theſe afflictions of ſuch Miniſters are alſo the heauier, in reſpect of the ioy and gaine of the Papiſts and other Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> Yea, all the premiſes are the more worthy the graue and wiſe conſideration of your High Court of Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the Lord threatened them that with their <hi>lyes made the hearts of the righteous ſad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>whom he had not made ſad,</hi> how heinous is it to make the hearts of them ſad, whom the Lord hath not onely not made ſad, but whom he hath alſo vſed as Inſtruments for much ioy and comfort in the Lord to many other?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> Do not the former iniuries alſo of 0536 0203 V 2 ſuch Miniſters redound to many other that make conſcience of their wayes,<note place="margin">The wrongs of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to other.</note> who are the more reproached with Puritaniſme? Euerie one almoſt <hi>that refraineth from euill maketh himſelfe a prey,</hi> and ſo both the name of Puritans, and alſo puritie it ſelfe is in deteſtation. Yea, by the former ſeueritie againſt ſuch Miniſters for not conforming, Religion it ſelfe is euerie where in the more contempt,<note place="margin">If. 59.16. Mark. 7.12.</note> and <hi>by mens traditions the Word of God is made of none effect:</hi> and all ſwearing, profaning of the Lords day, whoring, and drunkenneſſe, &amp;c. doe the more abound: and <hi>pride is to many as a Chaine, and violence couereth them as a Robe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 73 6</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> How alſo haue Poperie and Papiſts, both Ieſuites &amp; other Prieſts,<note place="margin">The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Poperie by the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</note> with their Diſciples encreaſed by the late and long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of preaching the Word? Yea how hath it encreaſed in all places (oh that I could except the Court it ſelfe) ſo likewiſe in all States? Amongſt the Common people: in the Gentry: in the Nobilitie? Yea are not ſome of the greateſt Nobilitie deepely dyed therewith? And whatſoeuer profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or ſhew they make by going to Church, &amp;c. Doe they not ſmell rankly thereof? Oh it is well if they doe not: euen well for all, but eſpecially for the Throne of Royall Maieſtie: Yea are not ſome of the Nobilitie, or their Heires
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1764:7"/>Apparant, of that ſtampe, that deſcended of Religious and Proteſtant Parents; ſome alſo, and diuers that haue lately been <hi>Nobilitati?</hi> Yea how doe the foreſaid Ieſuites and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries, and otherlike Prieſts euerie where ſwarme, and walke their Circuits, with the great walker and <hi>Peripatecian</hi> euen the Compaſſer of the Earth <hi>Satan,</hi> to deceiue, ſeduce,<note place="margin">Iob 1.7.</note> and make <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.13</note> 
               <hi>and two-fold more the Children of the Deuil then themſelues?</hi> Yea herein ſome <hi>Peripatecian</hi> Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites haue beene thought to haue had ſome Ladyes for their Curates. I will not ſay that ſuch Ieſuites haue beene, or are Vicars to ſuch Ladyes husbands: But whether they haue their deputations vnder ſuch Husbands Hands and Seales, that I leaue to ſuch Husbands themſelues to enquire. I haue no Commiſſion ſo to doe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> In conſideration of the former encreaſe of Poperie and Papiſts, it is the more high time for the Goſpel to be inlarged, and the Miniſters thereof to be incouraged. So much the more, becauſe the ſtate of the Miniſterie is yet verie weake, verie lamentable: both in reſpect of ignorant Miniſters, and alſo becauſe ſuch as are able to teach, are ſome exceeding lazie and idle, and ſome for their life and conuerſation verie ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous. Many Congregations likewiſe that haue ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters are rather content with them, then deſirous of better; neither ſo only, but by the meanes of ſuch Miniſters, they are altogether careleſſe of the meanes of their Saluation, not knowing what things do belong to their peace, and therefore well content to ſit ſtill in <hi>darkeneſſe and in the ſhadow of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as being ignorant of their danger thereby. So alſo they are apt to be drawne both into any Errour, and likewiſe into Rebellion againſt his Maieſtie, againſt his Poſteritie, and the whole Land. Though therefore there were twiſe as many able &amp; good Miniſters, as there are, yet all were litle enough.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> For all the foreſaid cauſes, both euerie one of the former Miniſters, and alſo all Congregations in the former miſerable condition, and euerie Member of the ſame, may ſay to your moſt Honourable High Court of Parliament, as <hi>Job</hi> ſaid to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1764:8"/>his Friends,<note place="margin">Iob 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>Have pittie vpon vs, haue pittie vpon vs, oh ye our Honourable, and Worthy, and Chriſtian Friends, for the Hand of God hath touched vs, in ſuffering our Miniſters to be taken from vs, or withholding ſuch from vs as we haue great need of.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 69.20.</note> 
               <hi>Reproach hath broken our Hearts; we are full of heauineſſe. We looked for ſome to haue had pittie on vs, but there was none. We are exceedingly filled with contempt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 123.3, 4</note> 
               <hi>Our Soule is exceedingly filled with the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe that are at eaſe: with the contempt of the proud.</hi> Yea, <hi>God hath deliuered vs to the vniuſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 16.11.</note> euen to them that are vniuſt by the Law of God and man.<note place="margin">Act 20.26. Iob 30.28.</note> Our Soules are ſtarued by keeping backe our Spirituall food, <hi>We goe mourning without the Sunne:</hi> by meanes whereof, <hi>we ſtand vp in the Congregation,</hi> as it were in the middeſt of your moſt Honourable Aſſembly, and cry vnto you for helpe and reliefe.<note place="margin">Lam. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>The Tongue alſo of the ſucking Children</hi> (new borne in Chriſt) <hi>cleaueth to the Roofe of their Mouth for</hi> (Spirituall) <hi>thirſt. Our</hi> (ſuch) <hi>young Children aske Bread</hi> (for their Soules) <hi>and there is no man</hi> (in many places) <hi>that breaketh it vnto them,</hi> yea many are readie daily to take it from them.<note place="margin">Lam. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>For theſe things we weepe: our Eyes, our Eyes, runne downe with water: becauſe the comforters that ſhould refreſh our ſoules are farre from vs: Our children are deſolate, becauſe our enimies</hi> (of our ſaluation) <hi>do preuayle.</hi> Therefore alſo as in this reſpect, many of vs may thus preſent our dolefull ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication generally to your moſt Honorable Senat, ſo why may wee not euery one with the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> in this our Famine of the Word cry out to his moſt excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and ſay,<note place="margin">2 Kings 6.26. Iudg. 18.24.</note> 
               <hi>Helpe my Lord oh King?</hi> If <hi>Michah</hi> made ſuch a wofull out-cry vnto the Children of <hi>Dan,</hi> as though he had loſt all that he had, becauſe <hi>they had taken away his Jdols, and Idolatrous Prieſts,</hi> oh how much more may we cry out againſt ſuch as haue taken away our faithfull Paſtors, or that will not ſet ſuch ouer vs, and ſay, <hi>What haue we elſe?</hi> For (alas) what haue we, if we haue none to breake the Bread of Life vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> As I doe moſt humbly beſeech his excellent Maieſtie prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, ſo ſecondly, I doe in all due ſubmiſſion intreat your
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1764:8"/>Religious Aſſembly to take no offence at this my mournefull complaint in the perſon of all other, ſith a chiefe Piller and Patron of the preſent <hi>Hierarchy (Hadrianus Sarauia</hi>) hath written, <hi>Praeſtaret nullos in Eccleſia eſſe Epiſcopos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In prolog. de triplici Epiſcopo.</note> 
               <hi>quam pro Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis habere lupos:</hi> ſuch as moſt Miniſters with vs in theſe daies are, partly in reſpect of their ignorance, partly in reſpect of their idleneſſe: partly in reſpect of their extreame auarice, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes crying, <hi>Giue, giue,</hi> and neuer ſaying, <hi>It is enough:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30.15</note> and partly in reſpect of their pride, intemperance, luxurie, and other their inordinate, looſe, and laſciuious conuerſation. And with theſe things, it is not vnworthy your wiſedomes to conſider a little the ſtate of the Vniuerſities; as being the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaries of the Miniſterie. Firſt, In that by ſubſcription vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to all ſorts in taking degrees, and euen to young ones that know not whereto they doe ſubſcribe, neither are able to iudge of the matters, as alſo that neuer are like to enter into the Miniſterie, many of great hope are diſcouraged, and doe rather leaue their preſent preferments, and betake themſelues to ſome other ſtate of life in the Countrey, then they will ſo burthen their conſciences. Secondly, In regard of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt that all ſober well minded and well diſpoſed young Students are in: of what towardneſſe ſoeuer and hope they be for Learning: yea how learned ſoeuer alreadie. Thirdly, In reſpect of the exceſſiue pride and brauerie of the moſt, though neuer ſo ſoberly brought vp before, and neuer ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to maintaine the ſame. Fourthly, For their great exceſſe in drinking and tobaccoing, in chambring and wantonneſſe: and in gaming, carding, and diſing, and in all manner of luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and laſciuiouſneſſe: yea alſo for their common ſwearing, ſwaggering, and almoſt all manner of prophanneſſe: hauing ſometimes the Maſters of the Colledges to be preſidents vnto them, in ſome of thoſe things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> To dwell a little longer vpon the effects of the former ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie againſt Miniſters,<note place="margin">Many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from the Miniſtery.</note> and the reſtraint of the preaching of the Goſpel, as though there were no need thereof, how many worthy men are thereby diſcouraged from the Miniſterie?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1764:9"/>How many haue no vſe of their gifts? How many are turned Lawyers and Phiſicians? or at leaſt are ſuch that otherwiſe would haue beene Miniſters? They cannot be charged to hide their gifts in a Napkin,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.18 and 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>neither to put their light vnder a Buſhell,</hi> for who may enter into the Church without a calling? or who may buy an Eccleſiaſticall calling with the leaſt ſinne? Or who for any ſuch calling may giue the leaſt wound to his conſcience?<note place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> Who alſo doe moſt obiect the hiding of their gifts to other? Euen ſuch as either haue no gifts at all them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or that doe neuer or ſeldome imploy them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> To proceed yet further,<note place="margin">Great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention by conformitie</note> may it pleaſe your moſt Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Court to conſider of the great diuiſion and contention made by them, that haue ſo much ſtriuen and contended for ſubſcription and conformitie, with them that only of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence haue not ſubſcribed and conformed, and that haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently teſtified their conſcience in that behalfe, ſo as before hath beene ſhewed. Touching this diuiſion and contention, where is it not? Betwixt whom is it not? The oppoſition of them that haue done the former wrongs vnto ſuch Miniſters, is ſtill ſuch, that although they had what they would from the ſaid Miniſters (to their skin in a manner) yet ſtill they enuie them, and as ſome haue accounted them as <hi>gangrens,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be cut off, neuer hauing written ſuch bitter things againſt the bloodie brood of the Papiſts, ſo ſome other are of the ſame minde, and would doe accordingly, did not the Princely grace and clemencie of his Maieſtie reſtraine them. This their minde they daily bewray by their continuall moſt bitter inuectiues againſt them. This contention is ſo hot, that young ſtriplings (in a manner) hauing gotten orders (as they ſpeake) feare not to diſgrace and contumeliouſly to vſe graue Diuines that were Preachers of the Word before their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were borne: and that not only publikely in Preaching, thinking they neuer preach well without railing: but alſo priuately in all meetings wrangling with them, and audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vpbraiding them with want of Learning, ſo ſometime alſo tanting them, as if they were not worthy to hold Booke
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1764:9"/>vnto them: and that becauſe themſelues may ſay any thing without controlment, but the other nothing without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> The foreſaid contention likewiſe is ſuch that the Miniſter is againſt the People, the People againſt the Miniſter, and one of the People againſt another, Kinſman againſt Kinſman, Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt Brother, Father againſt Sonne, Sonne againſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in word and practice: Huſband alſo and Wife ſomtime fall out one with another, about Miniſters ſubſcribing and conforming, and not ſubſcribing and conforming: What a rent likewiſe by ſubſcription and conformitie, and by ſtiffe maintaining of the Hierarchy hath beene made from our whole Church by ſome that therefore vtterly diſclaime the ſame, and denie it to be a true Church, &amp;c. affirming our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be no Miniſters, our Sacraments no Sacraments, &amp;c. How eaſily might an happie reconciliation be made by a wiſe and gracious reformation? Or at leaſt how iuſtly might they be puniſhed that after ſuch a reformation, and cauſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention remoued, ſhould ſtill remaine obſtinate?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> Neither is the former contention only betwixt our ſelues, but alſo betwixt vs and other Churches, euen by our great difference from them.<note place="margin">Eſt. 3.9.</note> Some with <hi>Haman</hi> thinking it not enough to lay hands on <hi>Mordecai</hi> at home, except they doe alſo by word and writing ſtrike through the ſides of worthy Diuines in other Countreys. As the Papiſts alſo ſearched the verie Graues for the bones of the Proteſtants long before dead, ſo it were to be wiſhed that ſome of our great Maſters and Patrons of our Hierarchy and Ceremonies had not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefully traduced the honorable names of <hi>Caluin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> and in them of diuers other, long ſince at reſt with the Lord, and that for their Iudgements in their Bookes againſt the ſaid Hierarchy and Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> It is eaſie to be ſhewed,<note place="margin">The former contention not iuſtly to be imputed to miniſters not confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, but to the vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie.</note> by the Iudgement of our beſt new Writers, our owne and other, that the foreſaid contentions are not to be charged vpon the foreſaid Miniſters, but vpon them that vrge ſubſcription &amp; conformitie: namely, out of Doctor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1764:10"/>
               <hi>Morton</hi> in the firſt part of his Catholike Apologie, <hi>Lib. 2.</hi> of the Notes of the Church, chap. 5. note 7. pag. 37. and that out of a Papiſt euen <hi>Caſſander,</hi> a kind of Mediator betwixt Papiſts and Proteſtants, pleading for a kind of reformation of ſome things in the <hi>Romiſh Church, Lib. Conſult. Articl.</hi> 7 as alſo of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other, euen maintaining the ſaid Hierarchy and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. The ſame is the Iudgement of <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, ſo alſo in his Booke againſt <hi>Richard Smith de calibatu &amp; votis,</hi> in his anſwer to the fourth Obiection of the ſaid <hi>Smith</hi> for the ſingle life and vowes of Prieſts. The ſame is the Iudgement of honorable <hi>Philip Mornaeus, lib. de Eccleſia, cap.</hi> 2. The like ſay many other, that affirme them to be contentious and Schiſmatikes, which are the occaſions of ſuch contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Schiſmes, by impoſing things that they ought not to impoſe, and that cannot be yeelded vnto with peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And that ſuch Miniſters, as ſubſcribe not and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, cannot be iuſtly charged as Schiſmatikes, and cauſers of contention. Maſter <hi>Parker</hi> one of the ſaid Miniſters hath learnedly, ſoundly, and plentifully ſhewed and proued this in his Booke of Symbolizing Ceremonies, <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 116.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> As the Lord ſhewed his diſpleaſure againſt <hi>Abimelech</hi> for a ſmall iniurie to <hi>Abraham</hi> ignorantly committed by <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euill to be feared.</hi> Gen. 20 3. 1 Sam. 15.3 2 King. 1.9</note> in reſpect that <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Prophet: and againſt the <hi>Amalekits</hi> for ſtopping the way, or withſtanding the entrance of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> into the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that 400 yeeres after they had ſo done: and againſt the two Captaines and their Fifties for comming only by the Kings commandement to fetch <hi>Elijah</hi> vnto the King;<note place="margin">2 Chr. 24.23, 24. 2 Chr. 36.16.</note> and againſt <hi>Ioaſh</hi> King of <hi>Iuda</hi> for putting <hi>Zechariah</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Iehoiadah</hi> to death: and vpon all the <hi>Iewes</hi> for their manifold contumelies, and other great iniuries againſt the Prophets from time to time, ſo the Miniſters of the Goſpel being greater then the Prophets, may we not feare ſome great Iudgement of God againſt vs for all the former hard dealing againſt them?<note place="margin">Mat. 23.37 Mat. 11.9.</note> Doubtleſſe we may feare the more, becauſe God ſpared not good King <hi>Aſa</hi> for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1764:10"/>impriſoning <hi>Hanani</hi> the <hi>Seer,</hi> for the word of the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered by him againſt <hi>Aſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 16.7. &amp;c.</note> for his relying vpon the king of <hi>Syria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> Your moſt Honorable Court may likewiſe be pleaſed to remember the great earthquake that followed the vniuſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> by the firſt <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Antiochia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socra. hiſt. Eccleſ. lib. 2. cap. 7. compared with Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Lib. 3. cap. 5. Theodor. lib. 5. C. 34 Sozomen lib. 8. C. 27 Socrat. lib. 6. cap. 17.</note> as alſo the like after for the like iniurie done vnto <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> And although vpon the ſame he were recalled home and reſtored to his place, yet not long after for the like cauſe, being againe banniſhed, the Lord pleaded his cauſe by a very extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hayle, and by the ſpeedy death of the Empreſſe <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> who had much exaſperated the Emperour <hi>Honorius</hi> againſt him, and finally that that is written of diuers ſtrange acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents after the death and martyrdom of <hi>William Gardiner</hi> (though but a marchant) mentioned in our owne booke of Acts and Monuments. In all which, ſo honourable, wiſe, and iudicious a Court need not any admonition to take heed of ſuch flatterers as ſhall ſay no ſuch thing is now to be feared. For yee all know them that heretofore in like caſes were wont to crye <hi>peace, peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere 6.14 and 8.11 Ezek. 13.18.</note> 
               <hi>and to heale the Lords people with ſweet words,</hi> to haue beene accounted falſe Prophets, as alſo <hi>woe</hi> was denounced againſt all them that did <hi>ſowe pillowes to the armeholes,</hi> and that did <hi>ſing a requiem to their owne ſoules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.3. Pſal. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>putting farre away the day of the Lord:</hi> as likewiſe that the Lord is now the ſame God in iuſtice againſt the ſame ſinnes that euer he hath beene, and the ſame <hi>beholder of miſchiefes and wrongs,</hi> and the ſame reuenger of iniuries done vnto his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors that euer he was. Yea, yee alſo know, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Miniſters hitherto mentioned, by their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries haue beene accounted no better then Aſſes, yet as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Lord rebuked <hi>Balaam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Balaam <hi>and his Aſſe.</hi> Num. 22.23. &amp;c.</note> for ſmiting his Aſſe when ſhe turned firſt out of the waye, wherein he would haue had her to goe, and then for lying downe vnder him, ſo the tyme may come, when the Lord will take their cauſe into his hands, and rebuke their riders the more for all the blowes they haue giuen them, becauſe euer ſince they haue beene
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1764:11"/>called to the Miniſterie, they haue done as good ſeruice to the Church as euer <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe had done vnto him. In the meane tyme they thinke they may as well complaine of the manifold blowes wherewith they haue been often ſmitten, as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe hauing her mouth opened by the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned of the ſtripes that <hi>Balaam</hi> had giuen her. Yea it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth they may the more complayne in that behalfe, becauſe they haue neuer ſo cruſht the foot of their riders, as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe had cruſhed his foot. If they haue, it hath beene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their riders haue gone that waye, for going wherein the Lord was angrie with them: or becauſe the ſayd Miniſters being ridden in ſuch a waye as where they could not turne, haue, (as it were) lyen downe, and not gone ſo farre as their riders would haue had them: as alſo becauſe they haue ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſuch Miniſters with their ſtaffe, and threatned to haue killed them, if they had had a ſword. In all which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they haue pleaded the ſight of the Angel of the Lord ſtanding in the waye with a ſword readie drawen in his hand, which they haue more feared then the ſtaffe or ſword of their riders.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> The wrath of God ſeemeth the more to be feared for the former hard dealing with ſuch Miniſters, becauſe of the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments threatned againſt the Princes of <hi>Iudah</hi> for their hard dealings with their ſeruants.<note place="margin">Ier. 34.16.</note> Euen ſo much the more ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſuch wrath to be feared, becauſe the Lord hath not only dignified his ſayd Miniſters with many great titles, and with the preaching of the beſt libertie, but alſo with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall effecting of ſuch libertie,<note place="margin">Galat. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>wherewith Chriſt hath made men free,</hi> and charged them not againe to be <hi>intangled with that yoake of bondage,</hi> that ſometime God himſelfe had made, much leſſe with the yoake of bondage made only by men, yea, at the firſt by the man of ſinne, and aduerſarie of Chriſt himſelfe. The chiefe Captaine feared to proceed againſt <hi>Paul</hi> becauſe he was free of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 22.24</note> Is nothing then to be feared for proceeding ſo farre and ſo long againſt ſo many Miniſters of the Goſpel that are free of Heauen it ſelfe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1764:11"/>and haue (as I ſayd) beene the meanes to make other alſo free thereof? How many fearfull things alſo followed all the Iewes for the hard dealing of their Clergie againſt <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> notwithſtanding the Princes of <hi>Iudah</hi> tooke his part and pleaded for him (as many Nobles of this kingdome haue done for ſuch Miniſters) as well as for other common ſinnes of that tyme?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> Not here to trouble you with repetition of that before touched, <hi>viz.</hi> which the Lord commanded both to be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,<note place="margin">Exo. 17.14 1 Sam. 15.2 Ierem. 4.19 2 Kings 22.11.</note> and alſo to be executed without any compaſſion againſt <hi>Amalek,</hi> neyther to ſpeake of the bitter complaynt of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> in the fore-ſight of iudgements comming, <hi>my bowels, my bowels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 34.19.24. Amos 6.1. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neyther alſo of his dolefull lamentation in that behalfe afterward in his Booke of Lamentations, nor of the teares and ſackcloth of <hi>Ioſiah</hi> at finding the Booke of the Lawe diſcouering ſuch future euills for the tranſgreſſions thereof, and to omit the woe threatned to them <hi>that were at eaſe in Zion</hi> and that liued in pleaſures, without remorſe of the <hi>afflictions of Ioſeph,</hi> as both generally wee doe now in <hi>England,</hi> and particularly many of the Prelats, not regarding eyther the heauie diſtreſſes of the Churches in <hi>France,</hi> or the hard ſtate of the moſt Noble and renowned Prince, and Princes <hi>Palatine</hi> though by nature as well as by religion wee are bound vnto them, and as we loue the kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus, ought to helpe them againſt their enimies leaſt wee incurre the curſe,<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.23. <hi>Iudgements already executed.</hi>
               </note> euen the bitter curſe of <hi>the Angel of the Lord againſt Meroz, and the inhabitants thereof</hi> for the very like cauſe. To omit (I ſay) all the former things, Oh that your moſt Honorable, and Chriſtian Senat would be pleaſed to remember and conſider the manifolde iudgements of God already executed ſince the reſtreint of the Word: the arming of all the foure elements againſt vs: of the fire not only often on ſome few houſes, but alſo on many great townes, to almoſt the vtter conſuming of them, of the aier, by great death of manie thouſands, almoſt in all parts of the Kingdome through the contagious peſtilence from the infection therof:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1764:12"/>of the water by many inundations to the drowning of many whole Pariſhes, eſpecially in the Weſt country: of the winds being of a fierie and aierie complexion and efficacie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing their force (as before ſo in this) by many late tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts both vpon the land, and alſo vpon the ſeas to the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king downe of come, the ſcorching and caſting downe of trees, the ouerthrowing of buildings, the loſſe of many great ſhipps, to the great hindrance (if not vndoing) of many marchants and other, and that according to the Lords like diſpleaſure againſt moſt worthy King <hi>Iehoſhaphat</hi> for his too much communion with <hi>Ahaziah</hi> king of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 22 48. 2 Chron. 20.37. Zeph. 1.3.</note> laſtly of the earth with the waters, by extreame froſts, and ſnow to the deſtruction as of ſome men, ſo alſo of many beaſts, and foules of heauen, and fiſh of the ſea, and other waters; with all which may be conſidered many vnſeaſonable tymes in other reſpects, and the extreame heat of ſome ſummers, ſuch as in ſome countries, men haue fallen downe ſtarke dead, as they haue followed their cattell, and as they haue laboured in hay time, and harueſt. Oh will ſome man ſay, theſe are old things, now paſt and gone, yea and forgotten alſo, as though they neuer had been. But alas, ſhould they ſo be? Wherefore then doth the Holy Ghoſt remember vs of the drowning of the whole world; of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha</hi> conſumed by fire from heauen, and many other the like? Yea, of the Lords not ſparing the Angels that kept not their ſtanding, but caſting them downe to hell, and binding them there with chaines, which was a thing much more ancient then all the former? And for reuiuing the memorie of thoſe iudgements aboue mentioned, Hath not the Lord this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent yeare, and theſe laſt yeares 1621 and 1622, done great things vpon the ſeas and vpon the Land, by the ſeas and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waters. Oh how many marchants ſhips haue beene taken by the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> pyrats, and otherwiſe loſt vpon the ſeas, to the vndoing of many thouſands, and the great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſhing of the whole Land? How much cattell alſo hath been loſt in diuers quarters by great and extraordinarie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1764:12"/>tydes of the ſeas and like floods of other waters? Finally how many houſes alſo haue by the ſame meanes been cleane caried away?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> But are the premiſes all? Not ſo. For hath not the Lord in the tyme of peſtilence come neere to the Court it ſelfe, in taking away ſome therewith that belonged thereunto. Hath he not cut of ſome great counſellers of ſtate extraordinarily, when neyther themſelues, nor any other any whit looked for any ſuch ſodayne hand of God vpon them? Hath not the Lord euer ſince the reſtreynt of the Word, whereby his owne Royall ſeed vpon earth ſhould haue beene dayly propagated, reſtreyned his bleſſing from our Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie for farther increaſe of his Royall poſteritie? Hath he not taken away his Royall iſſue borne a little before, and ſome ſince his comming hither? What cauſe alſo hath the Land to mourne for the death of moſt Noble Prince <hi>Henrie?</hi> Much more, much more then <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; all <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſo to mourne for the death of <hi>Abner</hi> as they did:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yea many may ſay Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> Prince <hi>Henrie, would God wee had dyed for thee,</hi> Prince <hi>Henrie,</hi> Prince <hi>Henrie;</hi> Had not the Lord remembred mercie in iudgement, by leauing vs moſt hopefull Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> we might yet mourne for the death of Prince <hi>Henrie.</hi> The greater the graces were of the late yong Lord <hi>Harrington</hi> (as Maſter <hi>Stock</hi> hath noted them in his Sermon at his Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and as many other could and can yet teſtifie) the greater was the loſſe of the whole Kingdome, by his death alſo: yet this was nothing to the former. May not alſo the death of our late Queene be reckoned amongſt other iudgements? The greater Gods mercie hath beene to his Maieſtie, and to the whole Land, in giuing and yet leauing ſuch a remnant of Royall ſeed by her, Prince <hi>Charles</hi> at home, and moſt vertuous Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> abroad (in many things reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our late moſt bleſſed Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe renowne will neuer die) as alſo in giuing ſo gracious and rich a ſeed vnto her, the greater iudgement (doubtleſſe) wee may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the death of Queene <hi>Anne</hi> her ſelfe to haue beene.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1764:13"/>Neither are we here altogether to forget the deadneſſe of all Trades, and alſo the great pouertie of moſt ſorts of People daily encreaſing thereby. In reſpect whereof though there haue beene ſuch a glut and plentie of Corne as hath not been knowne this many yeeres, yet the ſame is not to be accounted ſo great a mercie, becauſe it hath beene more hard for moſt Houſe-keepers to maintaine their charges then when Wheat was at a Noble a Buſhell, and all other Graine of price accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> 
               <note place="margin">The former iudgements to be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the reſtraint of the Goſpel.</note>As the former Iudgements cannot be denied to be for many great ſinnes, euerie where abounding; ſo alſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the Word, and the hard vſage of the Miniſters thereof, whereby themſelues and their Doctrine are in the more contempt and diſgrace with all ſorts of men, being a principall and maine cauſe of all other ſins, muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, to haue had a great attractiue vertue in drawing down the ſaid Iudgements vpon vs. In all former Ages vpon which the Lord inflicted his Iudgements, there were many other ſinnes prouoking the ſame: yet were ſuch Iudgements chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſcribed,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 36.16. Mat. 23.37</note> 
               <hi>to the mocking of his Miniſters, deſpiſing of his Word, and miſuſing his Prophets: and to the killing his Prophets and ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them that were ſent vnto them.</hi> There alwaies alſo haue been many great and heinous ſinnes in the Land; but there were neuer ſo vnknowne and new ſinnes, and ſo outragious abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations before, as haue beene ſince this maſter and capitall ſinne of ſuppreſſing the Word, and contempt of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters thereof. Moreouer though other ſins were alſo before, yet who can ſhew ſo many Iudgements to haue beene in ſo ſhort a time as haue beene ſince this mother ſinne of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of the Word? A mother ſinne alſo it may well be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, in reſpect of many great Errours hatched thereby, that either were not broached before, or that by all ſound Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, Biſhops, publique Diuinitie Readers in the Vniuerſitie, and other were condemned. Theſe new Errours to be ſtill maintained by ſome great Prelates (euen Biſhops) is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne, becauſe we haue ſent ſome Diuines to the laſt Synod
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1764:13"/>at <hi>Dort</hi> for ſuppreſſing the ſame. By theſe, how may future Ages be feared to be corrupted? And how ſhall ſuch actuall and mentall ſinnes be reſtrained? How ſhall all vertue and righteouſneſſe flouriſh?<note place="margin">Pro. 14.16 and 22.3. Pro. 29.18.</note> How ſhall men be prudent <hi>to hide themſelues from euils to come,</hi> but by the preaching of the word? <hi>Doe not the People periſh where there is no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſion?</hi> Though hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine policie and carnall wiſedome, by carnall and Machiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian men for State matters and preuenting of euils to come, be as much magnified, &amp; (as it were) adored,<note place="margin">Act. 8.11. and 19.28. Rom. 8.6, 7 Ierem. 8.9. Eph. 5.17.</note> as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> in <hi>Samaria,</hi> and <hi>Diana</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> yet all true Chriſtians know, ſuch wiſedome to be death to men, and enmitie to God, and no wiſedome at all: yea, meere fooliſhneſſe, and no better then madneſſe. Yea, it is the beſt policie to maintaine and ſupport ſuch Miniſters as being not onely faithfull and loyall Subiects themſelues, but alſo the teachers of all other to be: and <hi>the Chariots and Horſemen of the Kingdome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 2.12 and 13.14.</note> For certainly howſoeuer they be lightly eſteemed by their aduerſaries, yet they cannot be denied to haue done much good by their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie: yea many of their aduerſaries (I doubt not) will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it. The Congregations ouer which they haue beene ſet, and many other cannot but confeſſe it. I dare alſo boldly ſay, that many of your Chriſtian Court to which I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect theſe my Aduertiſements, will teſtifie it for themſeues, for their Children, for their Seruants. I thinke alſo I may ſafely ſay, that his moſt excellent Maieſtie, will grant thoſe Princely graces wherewith God hath enriched &amp; beautified his Royall heart to haue beene eſpecially wrought by ſuch Miniſters in his Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> as now are pleaded for, rather then by ſuch as doe moſt oppugne them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> 
               <hi>Laban</hi> and <hi>Nabal</hi> were both Birds of a Feather, and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (as it were) in euill, of the ſame conditions,<note place="margin">Laban <hi>and</hi> Nabal.</note> like to two Raine-bowes repreſenting one another in colour, the one by reflection hauing the ſame that the other, as the Letters of the one backward make the name of the other forward: yet the example of the one himſelfe, and of the Seruants of the other may prouoke all true hearted Chriſtians to reſpect the ſlate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1764:14"/>of the Miniſters before mentioned, and to doe what may be for them, eſpecially for the better libertie of their Miniſterie. <hi>Laban</hi> ſeeing the Iewels, Earings, and Bracelets which the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of <hi>Abraham</hi> had giuen to <hi>Rebecca,</hi> in behalfe of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Sonne <hi>Iſaack,</hi> the better to win her loue to be wife vnto him,<note place="margin">Gen. 24.31</note> ſpake thus to the ſaid Seruant, <hi>Come in thou bleſſed of the Lord: Wherefore ſtandeſt thou without? For I haue prepared the houſe: and roome for the Camels.</hi> How much more then ſhould any in any place of authoritie, and that haue both ſeene and alſo receiued the heauenly Earings and Bracelets that thoſe Miniſters as the Lords Seruants haue beſtowed vpon them and theirs to win them to Chriſt, and to make them fit for Chriſt, labour to bring ſuch Miniſters in againe whom others haue caſt out with their Wiues and Children? And that, as thoſe whom the Lord hath bleſſed, and made Inſtruments likewiſe to make others bleſſed. The Seruants likewiſe of <hi>Nabal</hi> hauing heard the churliſh, curriſh, and clowniſh words of their Maſter to <hi>Dauids</hi> Seruants ſent for ſome reliefe vnto him, reporting the ſame to their Miſtreſſe, pleaded alſo for <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5, 16.</note> and for his Seruants, ſaying, <hi>they had beene verie good vnto them, ſo long as they had been conuerſant with them when they were in the Fields:</hi> yea, <hi>that they had been a wall vnto them by day and by night to defend them all the while they had beene with them keeping Sheepe.</hi> How much more then may the Miniſters hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſpoken of be pleaded for, in reſpect that they haue neuer in truth done any hurt vnto any with whom they haue beene conuerſant, but haue beene a wall vnto them for their defence againſt principallities and powers, putting into their hands (yea into their hearts) <hi>the Sword of the Spirit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.17.</note> 
               <hi>the Word of God:</hi> and furniſhing them (inſtrumentally) with all other parts of the <hi>Chriſtian Armour?</hi> Yea touching <hi>Nabal</hi> himſelfe, though he were ſo hard and vngratefull towards <hi>Dauid,</hi> yet to his owne Sheepe-ſhearers he made a great Feaſt, a royall Feaſt,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.36.</note> 
               <hi>a feaſt like a King.</hi> Is it not therefore the more lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that they ſhould be ſo hardly dealt with, and brought to a morſell of Bread,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.27</note> that haue miniſtred vnto men the <hi>meat that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1764:14"/>periſheth not, but abideth to eternall Life?</hi> And that haue made a Feaſt to the Princes of the great King of Heauen and Earth, not <hi>of an hundreth and foure skore dayes</hi> only like to the moſt royall Feaſt of <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> or of <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſt. 1.3 Dan. 5.3</note> or of any other ſuch Monarch, but an euerlaſting Feaſt, according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of himſelfe whoſe Feaſt it was?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> With the former may be conſidered the great kindneſſe that <hi>Pharao</hi> ſhewed to <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and his Father and Brethren,<note place="margin">Gen 41.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and 47.5</note> for the Interpretation of his Dreames: For haue not the Miniſters reſtrained, depriued, &amp;c. Interpreted as great Myſteries con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning eternall Saluation, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Dreames were for the preuenting of the bodily Famine? The like may be ſaid of <hi>Dauid</hi>'s princely grace to <hi>Barzillai</hi> for his ſmall kindneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him when he fled from <hi>Abſalon</hi> (which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ind as a Subiect he was bound in dutie to haue performed) and vpon his death bed giuen in charge to be remembred by <hi>Salomon</hi> to the Sonnes of the ſaid <hi>Barzillai</hi> after the death of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19.31.33</note>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 2.17 2 Kin. 3.15</note> The great bountie alſo offered by <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> vnto <hi>Eliſha</hi> for directing him to doe that whereby he was cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his bobily Leproſie may here be well remembred. The particular application of both which examples, I leaue to your wiſe conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> It is not alſo vnworthy your moſt Honourable and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Court to conſider,<note place="margin">Many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable Miniſters wiſh the remoue of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</note> that many conformable Miniſters ſubmitting themſelues to ſubſcription and conformitie by the ſeueritie of other, becauſe otherwiſe they can haue neither imploiment of their gifts, nor maintenance, would be as glad of the remouing the things now hindring the free paſſage of the Goſpel, as the Miniſters ſilenced, and otherwiſe moleſted. For though they yeeld for the reaſons premiſed, and in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to doe good, yet they are of the ſame mind that other are of, and would teſtifie the ſame vpon aſſurance they might ſo doe without preiudice to themſelues.<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.42</note> 
               <hi>As many among the chiefe Rulers of the Iewes beleeued in Chriſt, but becauſe of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees they did not confeſſe him, leaſt they ſhould be put out of the Syndgogue</hi> (or rather) the Congregation; that is, leaſt they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1764:15"/>ſhould be excommunicated,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.22.</note> becauſe the <hi>Iewes</hi> had made ſuch a generall Canon againſt any man that ſhould confeſſe <hi>Ieſus to be Chriſt,</hi> ſo doe many worthy men conſent with the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſilenced, but feare of ſome Biſhops (vnmercifull indeed, as ſome are in ſignification of their name) they dare not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray their Iudgements for feare of the ſaid danger. Yea, I am perſwaded that ſome of the moſt reuerend Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, doe vnfeignedly deſire the reformation of ſome things that are the cauſes of the former troubles. Yea, I ſay more, that I knew a verie learned, reuerend, and renowmed Biſhop (not long ſince deceaſſed) that ſaid to a ſilenced and depriued Miniſter of his Dioceſſe ſuing vnto him for ſome enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Miniſterie that he would willingly grant his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, but he durſt not, becauſe he was a man vnder authoritie and muſt obey. But ſaid he, I will pray for you, that thoſe things may be remooued that doe hinder you, that we may all ioyne together againſt the common Aduerſarie, for it is high time.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> May it pleaſe alſo your moſt Honourable Court to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that your grace craued to further the free paſſage of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">The remoue of Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the whole Land. Can. 27. <hi>Eſt. 3.2.</hi>
               </note> and to remoue the hindrances thereof, doth concerne your ſelues and yours, and the whole Land, and not ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters onely, and that in reſpect of diuers Canons. Such is the Canon of kneeling at the celebration of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per (in the verie act of receiuing the Bread and Wine) not much vnlike the commandement of <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> for bowing the knee to <hi>Haman</hi> whereunto <hi>Mordecai</hi> would not yeeld, though thereby he hazarded his owne ſtate and the ſtate of all the <hi>Iewes:</hi> and though for his yeelding he might haue pleaded that he neither did it religiouſly according to the manner of the People,<note place="margin">Exod. 17.14. Deut. 25.17. Eſt. 3.1. &amp; 10. &amp; 9.24 <hi>Can. 98.</hi>
               </note> nor in contempt of Gods Commandement for warre and hatred on the part of the <hi>Iewes</hi> againſt the <hi>Amale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kits,</hi> whereof <hi>Haman</hi> was one (euen an <hi>Agagite,</hi> of the Kings Stocke) but only ciuilly in reſpect of the Kings command, ſtill keeping hatred againſt the <hi>Amalekits,</hi> though he gaue that ciuill outward reuerence vnto <hi>Haman.</hi> The like is the Canon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1764:15"/>againſt Appeales to any Iudge <hi>ad quem,</hi> in any caſe whatſoeuer, if the Aduerſarie may with any colour plead the other partie to be a Schiſmatike. Such is the Canon touching Diuorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Can. 4.6.7.8.</note> Such is the Canon for Excommunication <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> of euerie one that ſhall ſpeake any thing againſt any of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, or againſt any rights and ceremonies eſtabliſhed wherby men may be diſabled from making their Will, or their Wills may be fruſtrated, or at leaſt their Executors much moleſted. Such is the Canon or ſeueritie vſed for reſtraining the People from ſeeking the Word elſe-where, though they haue no preaching at all in their owne Pariſhes, or ſuch only as would grieue any Chriſtian heart to heare it.<note place="margin">Can. 18.</note> Such is the Canon for the ſuperſtitious &amp; ridiculous bowing of the knee at the name of Ieſus, to the diſturbance of the whole Congregation, and the hinderance, both of the Speaker or Reader, &amp; alſo of the hearer: whereas no ſuch thing is inioined at the name of God the Father, or of Chriſt, or of the Lord, or of our Sauiour, thogh this be all one with the name of Ieſus, &amp; the very mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therof. The like may be ſaid of diuers other canons:<note place="margin">Many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to our Lawes.</note> and although ſuch Canons may be ſaid, euen <hi>iure humano</hi> not to be lawfull, and therefore cannot be pleaded in any of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Temporall Courts, yet herein euerie man is not able to wage Law againſt their Aduerſaries. Although alſo ſome of the ſaid Canons were not perhaps agreed vpon by the greater part of the <hi>Conuocation,</hi> but onely hatched by ſome few great Prelats and caried out by ſtrong &amp; boiſterous hand, yet who may make queſtion of theſe things? Much trouble hath been and daily is by ſuch Canons, and more will be, if by your worthy Senat it be not preuented.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> 
               <note place="margin">Many wicked men haue more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie then mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpel.</note>Of the reſtraint alſo of the before pleaded for Miniſters from all benefit of the Law may not vnfitly be ſaid that of <hi>Ioel,</hi> touching the Famine of his time, <hi>Heare ye this ô Elders, and hearken all ye Inhabitants of the Land, whether ſuch a thing hath been in your daies or yet in the daies of your forefathers, &amp;c.</hi> Shall all blaſphemers, contemners of all goodneſſe, drunkards, &amp;c. haue the benefit of the Law, and ſhall ſuch Miniſters onely be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1764:16"/>ſo vile, as to be debarred from it? The lewdeſt man that is cannot be ſo eaſily diſpoſſeſſed of a poore Cottage of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhillings a yeere, as many worthy Miniſters haue beene cie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with their Wiues and Children from a Liuing of more then an hundred pound by the yeere: and that ſometimes for not obſeruing a Booke, neither eſtabliſhed by Law, nor inioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Canon, neither euer tendred vnto them; yea alſo without any preſentment in that behalfe. The old ſaying, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat Rex, currat Lex,</hi> importeth the ſafetie of Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to conſiſt much in the execution of Iuſtice;<note place="margin">Pro. 20.28. and 29.14.39</note> the which alſo agreeth with the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> Is it not likewiſe ſtrange, that common Players, by diuers Acts of Parliament condemned to be Rogues, and that are indeed the Lords of much miſrule, and great wickedneſſe, that theſe (I ſay) ſhould haue libertie to exerciſe their abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable trade condemned in all well ordered Commonwealths: yea with eſpeciall Command to all Officers for their ayd, yea further, that ſuch baſe perſons ſhould ſo <hi>debacchari</hi> againſt all ſorts, and diſgrace the greateſt Peeres in the Land: yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times alſo being bold with his high Maieſtie, vpon their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, much more with any Miniſters that they ſhall heare to ſpeake againſt their roguerie: and that ſuch learned and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters, no way ſcandalous in their life, ſhould haue their mouthes ſtopped? Moſt ſtrange eſpecially is it, that his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie, ſhould enlarge all Papiſts, and diſcharge them from Impriſonment and other penalties for any former of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and that without any ſubmiſſion to our Religion, and that yet the hearts of the Prelats ſhould be ſo hardned againſt their Brethren, as not to enlarge them, and diſcharge them from all puniſhments for their ſuppoſed offences: but ſtill to continue their ſeueritie againſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> Moreouer,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Examples to moue the Parliament</hi> Ier. 26.16 Ier. 38.9</note> your ſaid moſt Honourable Court, may the more boldly do the more for the enlargement of the Goſpel, and ſuch Miniſters thereof, becauſe of many other examples doing the like: Of the Princes and People of <hi>Juda</hi> pleading for <hi>Ieremiah</hi> againſt the Clergie of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Of <hi>Ebedmelech</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:1764:16"/>petitioning earneſtly for him to the King, and preuailing with the King, though a wicked King,<note place="margin">Ier. 39.26.</note> and therefore gratiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded by the Lord with grace for his deliuerance from the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> otherwiſe to all other mercileſſe: Of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 2. Eſt. 5.2. Ioſeph. de Ant. Iud. li. 12. cap. 2 Acts and Monum. printed 1596. pag. 554. Ibid. p. 38<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of <hi>Eſter</hi> with great danger of her life, of <hi>Ariſtaeus</hi> petitioning vnto, and preuailing with <hi>Ptolomeus Philadelphus</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> for ſetting at libertie an hundred and twentie thouſand Captiue <hi>Iewes,</hi> of the Nobles of <hi>Bohemia</hi> ſupplicating both twiſe to the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and alſo to the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> for <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> as alſo of the foure and fiftie Nobles of <hi>Morauia</hi> after the death of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Hus</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> writing an excellent Letter to the ſaid Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi> in defence of the ſaid two Martyrs: ſo likewiſe of the foure and twentie Nobles of <hi>Auſtria</hi> to <hi>Ferdinando</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sleidan lib. 14.</note> humbly ſupplicating for the free preaching of the Goſpel, and in their ſaid Supplication pleading many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent things, well worthy the obſeruation of all other of like place and ſtate:<note place="margin">Sleidan li. 25. &amp; 26</note> the like may be ſaid of their further im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie twelue or thirteene yeeres after for about two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred baniſhed Miniſters. Aboue all, moſt worthy obſeruation is the example of our owne moſt Noble King himſelfe, both in writing his royall and gratious Letters while he was King only of <hi>Scotland</hi> to our late renowmed Queene, Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> of bleſſed memorie, for Maſter <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Vdal,</hi> in the ſame cauſe for which the Miniſters hitherto men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned haue beene reſtrained, &amp;c. (as Maſter <hi>Cartwright</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teſtifieth in his Epiſtle dedicatorie to his Maieſtie before his Metaphraſe and Homilies vpon <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi>) both (I ſay) in writing his ſaid Letter, and alſo in writing lately to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoking of all Chriſtian Princes againſt the Pope, to whom and to whoſe Superſtitions from the greateſt to the leaſt, none are more abſolute aduerſaries then the Miniſters whoſe liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hitherto hath beene ſhewed to be ſo neceſſarie. Hath not his Maieſtie alſo written to the States of the <hi>Low-Countrey</hi> for the repreſſing of <hi>Vorſtius</hi> and all his Errours? The more we wiſh and deſire his ſaid writings to preuaile againſt the Pope
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1764:17"/>and againſt <hi>Vorſtius,</hi> and his Diſciples yet remaining, the more we may hope his Maieſtie will enlarge the Goſpel it ſelfe, <hi>the Word of Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.5.</note> within his owne Dominions. For ſuch as ones hatred is to Errour, ſuch is his loue to the Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> The more highly alſo that God hath commended the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the righteous,<note place="margin">Miniſters to be the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected for their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſake.</note> chiefly of Miniſters of the Word: tho more large promiſes he hath made to the praiers of ſuch; and finally the more he hath graced and magniſied ſuch prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with great and glorious ſucceſſe for priuate perſons; and eſpecially for Princes &amp; Kingdomes (euen ſomtimes wicked and vngodly.) The more is the Goſpel it ſelfe to be enlarged and the Miniſters thereof regarded for ſuch praiers ſake, not only in reſpect of the praiers of ſuch Miniſters themſelues, but alſo becauſe ſuch Miniſters with other, by the Goſpel preached teach all men to pray for all men, <hi>eſpecially for Kings and all in authoritie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie.</hi> And albeit ſuch Miniſters howſoeuer moleſted and wronged, may and ought notwithſtanding to ſay with <hi>Samuel, God forbid that we ſhould ſinne againſt the Lord and ceaſe praying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.23.</note> euen for them that doe moſt moleſt vs; yet alas who is ſo ſimple, as not to know, that the more kindly any are dealt with, the more they will be encouraged to pray with all alacritie, and cheerfulneſſe: and ſo the more gratious bleſſing is to be hoped for by ſuch praiers? For not only in liberalitie, but alſo in all other duties the Lord loueth cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.7.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> The free paſſage of the Goſpel without ſuch clogs as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto it hath been cloied with,<note place="margin">The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largment of Miniſters not preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</note> and the enlargement of the Miniſters reſtrained by the authoritie of his Maieſtie, as many of their aduerſaries haue pretended, will no waies be preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to the Honour of his Maieſtie himſelfe, or to the credit of the chiefeſt actors, in reſtraining either of the Goſpel it ſelfe, or the Miniſters thereof. Firſt, Becauſe <hi>them that honour God, God himſelfe will honour. As length of daies is in the right hand of wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30 Prou. 3.16 Prou. 4.8.</note> 
               <hi>ſo riches and glorie are in her left hand. She will exalt them that exalt her, ſhe will bring them to honor that embrace
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1764:17"/>her. Was not glorie departed from Iſrael, when the Arke of God was taken; wherein were kept the Tables of Gods Teſtimonies?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 4.21 Exo. 25.26 1 Sam. 25.32.</note> Secondly, It was no diſhonour but a great honour to <hi>Dauid</hi> to reuoke his words of Indignation againſt <hi>Nabal,</hi> at the bare counſell of a Woman <hi>(Abigael)</hi> and that before all his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers (euen foure hundred) in whoſe hearing he had before with great vehemencie ſpoken his ſaid words:<note place="margin">Pſ. 34 &amp; 52 &amp; 54 &amp; 56 and 57.</note> though <hi>Dauid</hi> were then a Prophet &amp; had before that written diuers <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and were a worthy Souldier, and alſo known to be the Heire Apparant to <hi>Saul,</hi> as annointed by the commandement of God, and therefore aſſured that he ſhould not by any meanes be intercepted of the Kingdome. Thirdly,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.4 compared with 19.19 Eſt. 3.8. Eſt. 8.5. &amp;c</note> Was it any diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to <hi>Dauid,</hi> yea rather was it not a great honour vnto him to cancell the gift he had made of all the goods of <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth</hi> vnto <hi>Ziba,</hi> and to returne them againe vnto <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth?</hi> Fourthly, Was it any great diſhonor to the great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> to reuerſe all that he had done at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Haman</hi> againſt all the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and to giue ſo large com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as he did, for reuenge vpon all their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies? I ſpeake not this as wiſhing the like euill to the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries of the ſaid Miniſters ſilenced and depriued. Farre be all ſuch euill with from me, from them, and from all other true Chriſtians: yea, all good be vnto them for Soule and Bodie: onely if it were no diſhonour to that mightie Emperour, not onely to reuoke his former Decree and Letters againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> granted to one ſo highly in his grace; but alſo to grant the like Commiſſion againſt their aduerſaries, much leſſe will the enlargement of the Miniſterie be any diſhonour to our Noble King, or any diſgrace to his Officers that haue ſilenced and depriued them: ſith they ſeeke not for, neither deſire any reuenge vpon any of their aduerſaries, but pray for them, and wiſh all good vnto them. The like may be ſaid of <hi>Zedekia,</hi> hauing before giuen power to his Princes againſt <hi>Ieremiah</hi> with great words, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ier. 38.5</note> 
               <hi>Behold he is in your hands for the King can deny you nothing</hi> (as now the aduerſaries of the ſaid Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters pretend they haue the like power from his Maieſtie to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1764:18"/>deale as they haue done, hauing no ſuch power by any Law) and yet afterward vpon the petition of one only (and he no naturall ſubiect) giuing a counter-commiſſion for the ſauing of <hi>Ieremiah</hi> and fetching him out of priſon.<note place="margin">Ier. 38.10. Exo. 32.10.12. Iudg. 10.13 Exo. 32.11</note> To conclude this argument; hath not God himſelfe oft denyed helpe to his people, and forbidden men to pray for them, or them to pray for themſelues, and yet for all that holpen them? Was this any diſhonor to his diuine Maieſtie? Yea rather, As <hi>Moſes</hi> pleaded the honor of God therein; and as other being (as it were) forſaken of the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.9.</note> 
               <hi>craued his helpe, and to be deliuered out of their trouble for the glorie of his name:</hi> And as <hi>Samuel</hi> aſſured the <hi>Iſraelits,</hi> being in great diſtreſſe and feare, <hi>that the Lord would not forſake them for his great names ſake, &amp;c.</hi> ſo the Miniſters before ſilenced,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.22.</note> and ſtill in great diſtreſſe doe hope they may now plead for the free courſe of the Goſpel, and for comfort, <hi>and to be made glad according to all the dayes, wherein they haue beene afflicted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.15</note> for the greater honor of all the States of <hi>Parliament:</hi> and for the greater glory of his gracious Maieſtie it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>As hitherto in the ſame priuiledge whereby other ſubiects preferre their complaints and cauſes, to the High and moſt Honorable Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> I haue exhibited the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer arguments for the enlargement both of the Goſpel it ſelfe, and of the Miniſters thereof hitherto moleſted, and like daily ſo to be, vnto the graue and wiſe conſideration of your ſayd Court, ſo now I will be bold vpon the ſame free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and libertie of other ſubiects, to exhibit alſo ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to your ſayd Court, which much likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne Gods glory, and the common good, both of Church and Common-wealth within his Maieſties Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> Firſt therefore I will beginne with Papiſts, to ſhew ſome reaſons for the better ſuppreſſing or conuerting of them,<note place="margin">Reaſons for ſuppreſſing or conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</note> as hauing mentioned them before. Now becauſe they are of diuers ſtamps, ſome plaine Recuſants and ſome Church Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, ſome obſtinat, ſome ignorant, and ſuch as are Papiſts, rather to pleaſe ſome other, then of any conſcience. May is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1764:18"/>pleaſe your Honorable Court to conſider of all theſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Open Recuſants, and Church Papiſts, are not much vnlike one to another.<note place="margin">Pſal. 55.20 21. Prou. 26.18 23.24.15 2 Sam. 3.27 and 20.10. Mat. 26 49 Luk. 22.47 48. Ier. 41.2</note> Only as a ſecret enimie is more dangerous then an open one, as is manifeſt by diuers ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces and examples of the Scripture. <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amaſa,</hi> being both vnawares ſlaine by a falſe kiſſe, of <hi>Ioab:</hi> as alſo our Sauiour by the like of <hi>Iudas:</hi> and <hi>Gedaliah</hi> with all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, being put to the ſword by the pretended friendſhip of <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> As (I ſay) ſecret enemies are more dangerous then open, ſo are Church Papiſts more dangerous then open Recuſants, becauſe vnder colour of comming to Church they are more hardly diſcerned. Notwithſtanding they that are wiſe may know them.<note place="margin">How ſecret Papiſts may be knowne.</note> Firſt by being from Recuſants ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly conuerted to come to our Churches and exerciſes of Religion; becauſe the kingdome of God is not like to <hi>Ionas</hi> his Gourd, but to <hi>a graine of mustard ſeed:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ionas 4.6 Matth. 13.31.</note> and hauing beene conuerted only by ſome priuat perſuaſions, or by preſent or hoped for kindneſſes of men, &amp;c. and not by any publike Miniſterie. Secondly, By their late and ſlacke comming to the Word, and by their looſe attention therunto, whiles it is preached, but ſpending the time in talking and whiſpering with other, or in reading of prayers, or of ſome Popiſh Booke. For <hi>he that is of God heareth Gods Word:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.47 1 Pet. 2.2</note> 
               <hi>he that is borne againe deſireth the ſincere Milke of the Word.</hi> Thirdly, By their priuat ſpeeches eyther for Poperie, or againſt the truth or the louers of it, as ſome of the <hi>Ephraimits</hi> were knowen not to be <hi>Gileadits</hi> by their tongues. Fourthly,<note place="margin">Iudg. 12.6.</note> By their Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and Seruants and companie; For <hi>Noſcitur ex comite qui non cognoſcitur ex ſe,</hi> and <hi>birds of a feather will flye togeather.</hi> Fifthly, By their coldneſſe in ſpeaking or doing any thing publikely for the trueth.<note place="margin">Luk. 7.47</note> For as <hi>to whom a litle is forgiuen he loueth little,</hi> ſo <hi>to whom much is forgiuen he loueth much.</hi> Sixthly and laſtly, (if they be great perſons) By their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of Papiſts to ſuch preferments as are in their power.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> 
               <note place="margin">All Papiſts dangerous.</note>All grounded Papiſts, Recuſant and other are ſo much the more dangerous, becauſe as Satan by little ſinnes preuayleth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1764:19"/>with men for greater, ſo do they by inſinuation into Princes for ſmall matters oftentymes bring their purpoſes to paſſe for greater. As no humane Lawes alſo will reclayme Papiſts without the libertie of the Word, ſo neyther will any cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie of Princes do them any good without ſeueritie. They can no more liue without treacherie, then without eating, drinking, and breathing. Frendſhippe doth rather harden then mollifie them. Theſe things are manifeſt by their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall treaſonable practiſes againſt our late moſt Noble Queene, and againſt our preſent dread Soueraigne, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe againſt other Princes in other Countreys. The more fauour hath beene ſhewed them, the more they haue lifted vp their heeles, againſt ſuch their fauourers. The more that other are for <hi>peace and ſpeake thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 120.7</note> 
               <hi>the more they are for warre.</hi> Many good Lawes haue beene already made againſt them, and are yet in force. But what difference is there betwixt no Lawes at all, and no execution of Lawes? Little, but this, that where there is no Lawe, there cannot in Iuſtice be any puniſhment: but where there are Lawes, there may be execution when God ſhall giue the Magiſtrates hearts ſo to doe. Some of the Lawes alreadie are for death of ſome offenders in that kind. Other are but <hi>pecuniarie,</hi> whether theſe alſo are not to be made capitall I leaue to the wiſedome of your Court to conſider by the expreſſe Law of God in that behalfe,<note place="margin">Deut. 13.1 &amp;c. Exo. 21.16 Deu. 14.19 and 20.18. and 24.7</note> againſt all intiſers to Idolatrie: as alſo by other Lawes for death againſt leſſe tranſgreſſions both of the Firſt, and alſo of the Second Table. And touching that place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.7. againſt men ſtealers, and makers of merchandize of them, who do ſo highly offend in this kinde as Papiſts, that ſteale men from God, from their Soueraignes and make mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize of their Soules to the Deuil? Do they not alſo rob men of their temporall goods, to enrich their Pope and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, whereby the kingdome of darkeneſſe may be the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt all other kings and kingdomes? Are not ſuch Papiſts murderers oftentimes of Princes, euen of their owne Religion? As alſo repentance of other ſinnes puniſhable with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1764:19"/>death, will not free men from death,<note place="margin">The Lawes of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> as alſo the due execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and good effect thereof, are worthy to be conſidered in this caſe.</note> ſo it is worthy conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whether repentance of Popiſh idolatrie, be ſufficient to diſcharge men from the puniſhment of death. Yea, there may be queſtion, whether they do truely repent of ſuch Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, that do not teſtifie the ſame by willing ſubmiſſion of themſelues to Gods Lawe for death in that behalfe. Yet for the tyme to come, death may be preuented, and increaſe of Poperie ſuppreſſed, if ſome ſharpe Lawe in the meane tyme be made for reſtreyning both of men and women from going beyond the Seas, and there becomming <hi>Ieſuits</hi> and <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiteſſes:</hi> as alſo of all here at home from yeelding any mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance vnto them in thoſe places.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> If notwithſtanding the premiſes vpon iudicious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of them, it ſhall be thought meet to ſhew them that now are or ſhall be mercie for life, yet being by their fruits knowen to be Papiſts, why ſhould they be admitted into Parliament for making of Lawes who themſelues will not obey, eyther other good Lawes of men, or the Lawes of God that are without all exception? Yea, why alſo ſhould they haue any authoritie in the Countrey, or offices or places of great worth in any Courts Temporall, or Eccleſiaſticall? Eſpecially it ſemeth vnfit for them to be of his Maieſties Priuie Countell, that haue taken ſo ill Counſell for their owne ſaluation, and will take no better. For how will they, or can they do any thing againſt Papiſts, that are ſuch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> Touching Recuſant Papiſts only refrayning from Church and hauing no priuat Maſſes at home, (if there be any ſuch) and being aboue 21 yeares of age, may it pleaſe your moſt Honorable Court to conſult of the confining them to their owne houſes, or ſome other, and reſtreyning them from all talke with any ſtrangers, but in the preſence of ſome ſound and ſufficient Miniſters, and of ſome Religious Iuſtice of Peace, as alſo of ſtinting them to a certayne number of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and of inioyning ſuch ſeruants of both ſexes to ſome common Badge openly to be alwayes worne, whereby to be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1764:20"/>diſcerned and ſhunned of all men; ſo alſo further, of taking their Children of aboue a certeyne age from them to haue Chriſtian education with kind vſage where their Popiſh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents or otherlike friends may haue no acceſſe vnto them, neyther the children themſelues know, where their parents are, and yet to haue ſufficient allowance from their parents according to their ſtate, ſuch parents alſo themſelues to haue mayntenance out of their owne demeanes: but the ouerplus to be conuerted to the Kings vſe, till the full age of ſuch children, and their open renowncing of Poperie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/> Foraſmuch alſo as all beleeuers are charged not <hi>to be vne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallie yoaked with vnbeleeuers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Againſt mariage with Papiſts.</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14 Exo. 34.16 Deut. 7.3 Gen. 6.2 &amp;c. Ezr. 10.14 Neh. 13.26 1 Kings 16 29.30.31 2 Chr. 21.3 1 Kings 11 1.4 Deu. 22.10 Matth. 7.6 cha. 15.26. 2. Pet. 2.22 P.M. in 1. King. 3.1. and 11.1. and loci com. claſs. 2. p. 149. Cal. Epiſt. 103.104.299.</note> and the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> were often forbidden to make mariages for themſelues or for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with any of the Heathen Nations bordering vpon them, and that all other ſinnes, for which the Lord drowned the whole world, but eyght perſons, are attributed to the maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the ſonnes of God (that is profeſſors of the worſhippe of God) with the daughters of men, that is of the Heathen and Idolaters: Foraſmuch further, as for this ſinne <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> cauſed ſuch of the <hi>Iewes</hi> as had made ſuch mariages, and had alſo children by ſuch mariages, to put away their wiues: as alſo that ſome kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are condemned for marying with Heathen women: and ſo likewiſe of the kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> for like mariages with the daughters of the kings of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and that the fall of <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe is aſcribed to the like cauſe, not only by <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in the place before alleaged, but alſo elſe-where. And againe, foraſmuch as the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> might not plowe with an Oxe and an Aſſe togeather, and therefore much leſſe Chriſtians may ioyne themſelues in mariage with Idolaters, ſuch as all Papiſts are in the higheſt degree: And yet againe, foraſmuch as we may not giue holy things vnto Dogs, nor caſt our pearles before Swine, and therfore much leſſe giue our ſelues to ſuch as are called Dogs and Swine: And further, foraſmuch as <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Caluin,</hi> with other ſound Diuines and diuers both ancient Fathers and alſo Councels haue written and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1764:20"/>much againſt mariages of Proteſtants with Papiſts, Is it not well beſeeming the wiſedome of your moſt Honorable Court by ſome ſeuere Law to reſtreyne ſuch mariages for euer hereafter within this his Maieſties Dominion, that ſo there may be the leſſe feare of ſuch increaſe of Poperie for the times to come as lately hath beene?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> Touching the ſeueritie before mentioned againſt Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants, and Church Papiſts,<note place="margin">Mungrill Papiſts.</note> may it pleaſe your Honorable Court herein alſo to conſider of Mungrill Papiſts, halfe fiſh, halfe fleſh; neyther fiſh nor fleſh, nor (as we ſpeake) good red herring: which ſometyme indeed come to Church to auoyd the pennaltie of former Lawes, but neuer come to the Supper of the Lord, but at ſuch tymes as men are ſpecially inioyned therunto, do flutter vp and downe, and ſhuffle from place to place, where they may beſt lurke, and ſo receiue not in ſeauen yeares togeather, if euer at any tyme: pretending for themſelues (being any where called into queſtion) ſome fuites of Law, or ſome other ſuch ſleeueleſſe excuſe. Neyther alſo are the familiar acquaintance of ſuch Papiſts altogeather to be forgotten: what alſo if it ſhould pleaſe your Chriſtian wiſedomes to make ſome Act for the fruſtrating of the laſt Wills and Teſtaments of ſuch as hauing pretended themſelues Proteſtants in their health, in their ſickneſſe vnto death ſhall profeſſe themſelues <hi>Romane Catholikes,</hi> as alſo make voyd what ſoeuer former Act they had made for diſpoſing of their ſtates, or any part thereof: and their ſayd ſtates to be eyther con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcate to his Maieſtie, or tranſlated to their next kindred, that had giuen good Teſtimonie of their being ſound Proteſtants: with this <hi>Prou ſo</hi> notwithſtanding, that vpon their reuolting to Poperie, euery ſuch Act to be voyd? for the bodies alſo of ſuch ſo deceaſſing to be buried in ſome ignominious manner, and in ſome place of reproach? Foraſmuch likewiſe as many Purſiuants ſent to ſearch the houſes of ſuch Papiſts, ſeeme at the firſt much to bluſter, till they meet with ſome Siluer drops for calming their tempeſts, were it not meet that this ſhould be preuented?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1764:21"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/> In all theſe things I prouoke not to crueltie, but to Iuſtice: ſuch as whereby <hi>a King maintayneth his countrie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29.4.</note> it being a ſpeciall part <hi>of a wiſe King to ſcatter the wicked, and to cauſe the wheele to go ouer them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21.3. 1 Sam. 15.22. 1 Kings 2.46. Ioſh. 7. 2 Sam. 21.1, &amp;c.</note> and the doing of ſuch iuſtice <hi>beeing more acceptable to the Lord then ſacrifices: and the throne of Salomon</hi> being then ſayd to be <hi>eſtabliſhed in the hands of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> when he had executed iuſtice, euen vpon his brother <hi>Adoniiah,</hi> and vpon <hi>Ioab,</hi> and <hi>Shimei.</hi> Did not <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo fall before little <hi>Aie,</hi> till iuſtice was done vpon <hi>Achan</hi> for his ſinne ſecretly committed? And was there not a famine in all <hi>Iſrael</hi> till <hi>Dauid</hi> had granted iuſtice againſt ſeauen ſonnes of <hi>Saul,</hi> for his ſinne againſt the <hi>Gibeonits,</hi> which had beene the cauſe of the ſayd three yeares famine? How was the Lord diſpleaſed with <hi>Saul</hi> for his mercie to <hi>Agag?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 1. Kings 20 42. Num. 33.55. Ioſh. 23.13 Iudg. 2.3.</note> And with <hi>Ahab</hi> for letting <hi>Benhadad</hi> a king of another Nation <hi>go out of his hands, whom he had appointed to die?</hi> Were not the <hi>Canaanites</hi> alſo contrarie to Gods commandement ſuffered by the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, prickes in their Eyes, and thornes in their ſides?</hi> O right Honorable, I humblie beſeech you to conſider that the <hi>Amalekites</hi> withſtanding only the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> as they were going to the earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and the <hi>Aramites</hi> that oppugned only their outward ſtate, and the other before mentioned were not ſuch aduerſaries as the Papiſts be, that are all members of the Man of Sinne,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.3 Apoc. 18.20.21. Apoc. 19.1 &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>the Child of Perdition,</hi> who cannot eſcape that horrible deſtruction that the Lord hath threatned, wherin men and Angels ſhall reioyce; and which are enimies to the euerlaſting ſaluation of all Gods people. Seueritie therefore againſt obſtinate Papiſts, is no crueltie, but great honor to God, and great mercie to our Soueraigne, to his Royall Poſteritie, to all his Kingdomes, and to all ignorant Papiſts themſelues. Worthy of euerlaſting remembrance is the gracious promiſe of God vnto <hi>Iehu</hi> for that that he had done to <hi>Iezabel</hi> and the reſt of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and their adherents,<note place="margin">2 Kings 10 36.</note> and to all <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt diligently executed that which was right in mine Eyes, and haſt done to that houſe of Ahab according to all that was in my heart, therefore
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1764:21"/>ſhall thy ſonnes ſit on the throne of Iſrael to the fourth generation.</hi> O the flouriſhing ſtate of this Kingdome, and the great honor of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in all other Kingdomes, with her admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable proſperitie, that would not vouchſafe a good counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to any knowne Papiſts. Many curſes ſhe had from the Father of Papiſts at <hi>Rome,</hi> and from his Imps here at home, <hi>but the ſame being cauſeleſſe came not to paſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 26.2</note> ſo did not their practiſes againſt her: Yea, ſhe and her people proſpered the better at home, and againſt all forein Enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> Let it not ſeeme ſtrange, right Honourable worthies, that I haue beene ſo plentifull in this argument.<note place="margin">The inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of Papiſts ſince the Powder-Treaſon.</note> By the helliſh Powder treaſons which ſhould haue deſtroied good and bad (that Hell it ſelfe doth not) a man, a meere reaſonable man, much more a man inſtructed in the Word of God, would haue thought, that all Poperie and Papiſts, would here and elſe-where throughout the Chriſtian World, as alſo with the Heathen themſelues, haue been had in perpetuall deteſtation, and euerlaſting execration. But it is one of the greateſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the World, that euer ſince Poperie hath the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed: and that, not amongſt perſons only of low degree, but of high and Noble ranke: as alſo that Papiſts old and new haue been more inſolent, and lifted vp their hornes high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then euer ſince the bitter daies of the late bitter Queene <hi>Mary:</hi> as if by the ſaid moſt diueliſh Conſpiracie, both Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie and Papiſts had preuailed with his moſt excellent Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and won grace and fauour with him; the which God forbid that any true hearted Chriſtian, and loyall Subiect, ſhould euer haue cauſe to thinke, or imagin. The former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie likewiſe of the Papiſts (or at leaſt of ſome of that faction) is now growne to that heighth, that ſuch true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and loyall Subiects, as before I mentioned, may now feare the companie of any whom they know not, either tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling by the High-way, or in any other place. Not long ſince, a luſtie young gallant, of no ſmall place (if perſons and ſtate may be iudged by Apparell, and Attendance) falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to companie of a meane man in the way, yet of good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1764:22"/>and religiouſly affected, and by ſpeech finding hint ſo to be, for a while ſoothed him vp, ſpeaking as he ſpake, and commending preaching as he did: but at laſt he vnmaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked himſelfe, and by diuers words ſhewed himſelfe in his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours to be a friend of Poperie; and not only an aduerſarie, but an enemie to the Goſpel, and of the preaching thereof: verie roughly breaking forth into theſe bloodie words, ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the bloodie Religion of the Scarlet Whore, and ſaying, It were a good deed to ſheath my Sword in thy body. O right Honourable doe not ſuch things preſage ſome further fore to be breeding? Is it not time to looke to ſuch? And haue not all well affected to the Goſpel, to his Maieſtie, and to his Kingdomes need to pray much, and to looke to themſelues, and to be wiſe as Serpents, and in their trauels and elſewhere to beware of ſuch Crocodils?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> In all the premiſes for more ſeueritie againſt obſtinat Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſant Papiſts,<note place="margin">Why no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath been ſpoken againſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration.</note> eſpecially known to haue Maſſes in their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the time to come, or to goe to Maſſes elſe-where, I haue ſpoken nothing againſt tolleration: Firſt, Becauſe if the premiſes ſhall take place, there needeth nothing in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Secondly, Becauſe his Maieſtie hath heretofore by the Lord Chancellor then being publiquely and graciouſly in his Court of Starre-Chamber ſignified his Princely reſolution to the contrarie: and that if he knew his Princely Sonne would encline that way, he would doe his beſt endeuour to diſinherit him. Thirdly, Becauſe he hath not long ſince, but euen lately almoſt, cauſed certaine Diuines to ſignifie as much in their publique Sermons at <hi>Paules</hi>-Croſſe in <hi>London.</hi> Fourthly and principally, Becauſe the ſame is teſtified by that moſt learned and reuerend Biſhop now Prelat of the Garter, in his learned anſwer (intituled <hi>Tortura Torti</hi>) to a Booke of one that called himſelfe <hi>Mattheus Tortus,</hi> who wrot his Booke againſt the Apologie of our Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie.<note place="margin">In the end of page 81 and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of page 82.</note> In this anſwer to the ſaid Book of the ſaid pretended <hi>M. Tortus,</hi> the ſaid reuerend and learned Father writeth thus <hi>verbatim,</hi> word for word, <hi>Nec in eo Regi audiendus, quòd conſilium dat,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1764:22"/>de Religione liberè habenda. Integrum hoc iam illi non eſt. Nam (quod eum ea qua decet reuerentia dictum volo) non ſemel periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus ſit, quin bis ſi te audiat. Qua enim (ſi qua eſt fidei bis datae conſcientia) vel conſcientia, vel fide ferret in regnis ſuis ritus veſtros vel vſum eorum publicum, qui ſuſcepta primum Scotiae, ſuſcepta dein Angliae corona regia, vtrobi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſolenni ritu deo iuſturandum praeſtitit, de conſeruanda in ſtatu ſuo illa colendi Dei formula, nec alia, quam quae in regnis ſuis tum publice recepta, &amp; vtriuſque gentis legitus ſtabilita eſſet. Quarum etiam ſe tum legum quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> non minus quam religionis ſanctiſſimè in ſe ſuſcepit defenſorem fore. Eo autem conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium hoc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uum tendit vt nouator ſit, vt periurus, vt vterque ſit. Eſſet enim vterque, ſi vtroque hoc tam graui crimine, vel coronae ſuae, vel etiam vitae ſecuritatem redimeret. Hoc vero quam a ratione prorſus alienum, tu lector iudica: Regi noſtro praeſertim, cui nulla hic apud nos periurij diſpenſatio ſperanda: cui nulla de Pontifice opinio, quòd tam ſit omnipotens, vt ſuſcepti eum bis iuramenti religione poſſit exoluere.</hi> Theſe are the verie Words of the ſame moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Writer: the Engliſh whereof, I leaue to the Learned of your moſt Honourable Court. The premiſed Teſtimonie conſidered, What loyall Subiect, can ſo baſely, or wickedly conceiue of h s Maieſtie, as that he ſhould euer yeeld to a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of that damnable Religion, againſt which he hath ſo often written, proteſted, and ſworne? So much the leſſe, are all true Subiects to conceiue any ſuch thing, becauſe by a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, as things now ſtand, not onely the Kings Maieſtie himſelfe ſhould be guiltie of the crimes mentioned in the former teſtimonie; but alſo all the Iudges of the Land, who are all ſworne to the execution of the Lawes alreadie enacted againſt Poperie and Papiſts: neither ſo only, but alſo all other Iuſtices of the Peace in the Countrey; all Maiors, Bailifes, and other chiefe Magiſtrates in all Cities and other Townes Incorporate. The forme alſo of Iuſtice in adminiſtration of Oathes, to Iurors, &amp;c. ſhould be changed. Alas, alas, What a confuſion would this make? And what might all the Land feare for ſuch doing? If the Lord will not hold him guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that any way taketh his Name in vaine, What may be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1764:23"/>feared when all the Magiſtrates of an whole Kingdome ſhall be guiltie of the ſame in the higheſt degree?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> 
               <note place="margin">Ignorant Papiſts.</note>Touching ignorant Papiſts, oh that ſome order might be taken for the reclaiming of them, by louing, kind, and diligent inſtruction by men of diſcretion, and wiſedome well fitted ſo to doe. Certainly the neglect hereof hath beene great, and ſomewhat ſcandalous to the State. Many haue beene greedie of their Money, and readie to beg the <hi>pecuniarie mulct</hi> of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence from Church. But alas who hath by good inſtruction laboured to bring them to Church, and to the ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth? Something likewiſe might haue beene inſerted for diſarming of Papiſts: but becauſe ſomewhat hath beene done in this kind, therefore I ſay the leſſe, onely order would be taken for renewing thereof yeerely, and for better ſearch of their houſes in that behalfe without any foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of any ſuch matter, whereby to conuey their Armour to their Farmers, or other Friends, or hide them in the Ground, or put them into Hogſheads, or Pipes, as if the ſaid Veſſels were full of Wine or Beere.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> 
               <note place="margin">Againſt Oathes.</note>The abounding of Oathes and Blaſphemies in this Land, notwithſtanding the manifold Commandements and fearfull threatnings of God againſt theſe ſinnes, and alſo the pride that men take in theſe ſinnes,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.1.2. Zech. 5.2. Ier. 23.10.</note> would require ſome thing to be ſpoken of them, leaſt we partake of the Iudgements belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto them. But hearing ſome ſpeech to haue been alreadie for ſome order to be taken for repreſſing of them, I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare all further ſpeech in that behalfe. Onely touching the Oath <hi>Ex officio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Oathe</hi> Ex officio</note> and the Oath tendred to Churchwardens, and Sidemen, as the firſt hath been largely declared by diuers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned iudicious Lawyers to be againſt the Lawes of the Land, eſpecially by that renowmed Gentleman, Maſter <hi>Morris,</hi> late Attourney in the Court of Wards: and is knowne ſo to be to many of your Honourable Court: as alſo the ſame hath been condemned openly in Weſtminſter Hall, by the Iudges of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Bench, euen to be againſt Law, Reaſon, Religion, and Conſcience, none but Time-ſeruers
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1764:23"/>daring to denie the ſame, ſo touching the other, Maſter <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> a learned Lawyer, and Iuſtice of Peace, by the authoritie of that ancient Iudge, Maſter <hi>Fitz-Harbert,</hi> in his <hi>Natura breui,</hi> hath in his directions for Iuſtices of Peace in giuing their Charges at Quarter Seſſions, ſet it downe for a ſpeciall Article to be enquired, whether any Ordinaries in their Courts doe impoſe the ſame. <hi>viz.</hi> Any Oathe to any of the Kings Lay people in any cauſes ſaue only in matters Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, and Matrimoniall. The ſame alſo to be contrarie to Law is further euident by the expreſſe words of the Regiſter, that hath the grounds of our Law, and the forme of all Writs for Law. The daily impoſition notwithſtanding of this Oath in all Eccleſiaſticall Courts by all Ordinaries, being troubleſome to many tender conſciences, if it might pleaſe your moſt Honourable Court to take ſome order therein, it would doubtleſſe be a meanes of much peace, and great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to many good Chriſtian Soules. That ſome obiect Churchwardens &amp; Sidemen not to be meere Lay men, many Lawyers can eaſily anſwer. And how can they be but Lay men (as things now ſtand) that are neuer accounted of the Clergie, that haue no Eccleſiaſticall ordination, that enioy no benefit of the Clergie, but only that which euerie one that can but reade enioyeth in ſome caſes of Felonie. The taking of this Oath is the more troubleſome, becauſe the Articles are ſo many, and variable according to the varietie of Ordinaries, of Times, of Dioceſſes. For ſometime one and the ſame Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries doe differ in their owne Articles. The cuſtome alſo of mens ſwearing, and forſwearing themſelues herein maketh them the readier to periure themſelues in other matters. To this point of the Oath <hi>Ex officio,</hi> eſpecially miniſtred vnto Churchwardens, may be referred all ſuch Articles as concern matters not belonging to Eccleſiaſticall Courts. Such is the Article for not paying rates to the Poore. The which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome Eccleſiaſticall Iudges haue acknowledged not to belong to their Courts, yet ſome poore men being preſented by vertue of that Oath for not paying haue beene
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1764:24"/>much moleſted, and at the laſt alſo excommunicated. The like may be ſaid of ſome other Articles throughly examined.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> 
               <note place="margin">Againſt Witches.</note>Againſt thoſe that are called good Witches, ſome order to be taken were the better, becauſe by ignorant and irreligious people, they are not ſhunned, but rather honoured. Thoſe that are accounted euill Witches, are puniſhed, but theſe are recompenſed as if they were indeed,<note place="margin">Act. 8.10.</note> as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was eſteemed to be in <hi>Samaria.</hi> The other by the Deuil bewitch the bodies and goods of men: theſe by the ſame Deuil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching the minds and ſoules of men, doe more hurt then the other. They vſe good words, but without vnderſtanding, and ſuch as are not appointed for working ſuch good works. Such good Witches alſo for the moſt part are void of all other good workes, and moſt profane, irreligious, and ignorant of Gods Word: and contemners of all exerciſes of Religion. In their workes alſo they reſpect not Gods glorie, but their owne gaine: working alſo either without any other meanes, then only words, or by ſuch meanes as haue no vertue in them for working ſuch things: but rather the contrarie, yet be vſed by them only to cloake their wickedneſſe, &amp; to bleare the peoples eies. There is alſo another kind of Witchcraft more ſecret then the former, and yet much worſe and more dangerous, verie hard alſo to be diſcerned, yet I doubt not, but ſuch as may be found by your wiſedomes ſeriouſly applied to the ſearching of it, &amp; the effects whereby it may be diſcerned. This is that inchanting of the mind ſuch as it ſeemeth <hi>Simon Magus</hi> vſed in making the <hi>Samaritans</hi> thinke, <hi>he was the great power of God:</hi> ſuch as whereto <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemeth to allude when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>O fooliſh Galatians, who hath bewitched you.</hi> God indeed ruleth the heart: yet by this meanes ſometimes in his Iuſtice, as well as by other: giuing the Deuil power as well to worke vpon the mind as vpon the bodie: Was it not he to whom the Lord gaue power, both to enter into <hi>Ahabs</hi> falſe Prophets to lye vnto him;<note place="margin">1 King. 22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> and alſo into <hi>Ahab</hi> himſelfe, to beleeue the ſaid falſe Prophets? Who but he, firſt bewitched (as it were) our firſt Mother <hi>Ene</hi> (hauing no inward euill of her ſelfe) to<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:1764:24"/>eate of the forbidden Fruit? If he had not had ſome ſecret footing within, he could neuer haue ſo preuailed by all his outward temptations.<note place="margin">1 Chro. 21.1. &amp;c.</note> How alſo did Satan <hi>prouoke Dauid to number Iſrael,</hi> but by his ſecret working inwardly? It is alſo reported of <hi>Cyprian</hi> that before his conuerſion he tryed by Magike to draw a young Virgin to haue committed filthineſſe with him, though the Deuil himſelfe confeſſed he could not preuaile becauſe of her Faith. Neither he by the Deuil, nor the Deuil at his requeſt would haue attempted it; but that both thought it might be done. And no doubt, but that by this meanes mariages are made of ſome, the one partie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch meanes vtterly abhorring the other, and after mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age ſhewing that they neuer maried in any true loue. Here I beſeech you giue me leaue to remember you of that, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Tyndal</hi> writeth in his Practice of Prelats, of <hi>Charles Maine</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and created Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi> by Pope <hi>Adrian.</hi> This <hi>Charles</hi> ſo doted in his old age vpon an old Harlot, by meanes of an enchanted Ring vpon her finger, that he could neuer endure her out of his ſight. Yea, ſhe dying, he embalmed her, and caried her in a Coffin with him whither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he went. At laſt his Lords being wearie thereof, and ſuſpecting ſomewhat, opened the Coffin, and found the Ring vpon her finger: which one of the Lords tooke off and put on his owne finger. After this, <hi>Charles</hi> left his dotage vpon her, and doted as much vpon that Lord: but the Lord being in time wearie thereof, doubted ſome euill to be in the Ring, and therefore tooke it off, and threw it into a Well, at <hi>Acon</hi> in <hi>Douchland,</hi> in a foule Mariſh; where notwithſtanding the ſaid <hi>Charles</hi> alwaies after remained, and built a goodly Monaſterie in worſhip (as they vſe to ſpeake) of our Lady. Pardon me (I humbly beſeech you) if herein I haue beene too tedious. For it is well worthy your graue conſideration, as the which may be a thing dangerous, not only to ſome priuate &amp; meane perſons, but alſo to other of great eminencie, and therefore alſo in them to whole Countreys. In which reſpect, if by your wiſedomes ye ſhall take ſome order to preuent it, ye may
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1764:25"/>doe greater good thereby, then many can conceiue, and for the which many may haue the more cauſe to bleſſe God for you. Though ſuch ſhallow heads as mine owne and ſome others, cannot eaſily ſee how it may be preuented, yet I doubt not but that your wiſedomes will by deepe conſideration of it ſee ſome meanes either to preuent it, or ſo ſeuerely to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it being made euident, that afterwards none ſhall ſo dare to offend in this kind as before.<note place="margin">Exo. 22.18 Deu. 10.11</note> Surely that wiſe and iuſt God that hath ſo often and ſtreightly commanded no Witches to be ſuffered to liue, hath alſo giuen wiſedome to ſome for finding theſe out.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> 
               <note place="margin">For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of the Lords day.</note>For the Religious obſeruation of the Lords day, many good motions haue heretofore beene made in Parliaments which alwaies (as hath been reported) haue been moſt hindred by ſuch as ſhould moſt haue furthered them: and that becauſe they haue more loued their owne eaſe and pleaſure in eating, drinking, and playing, then the glorie of God, or Saluation of his People. Therefore ſuch haue pleaded for libertie, in wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, bowling, carding, and tabling, more then for preaching or hearing Gods Word. Oh therefore that your Honourable Court would now at the laſt take ſome order for reformation of all abuſes of this day, by gaming, buying, and ſelling, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelling, eſpecially of common Cariers by Horſe, and by Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, or Carts, &amp;c. The neglect of this day is the neglect of all duties, and plainly argueth a profane man. This day cannot be throughly ſanctified without diligent preaching forenoon and afternoone: or at leaſt a profitable Sermon in one part of the day, and good catechiſing, and plaine teaching the Principles of Religion in the other part: the extreame igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of all ſorts and of all ages neceſſarily requiring the ſame. Such as plead one Sermon enough to be meditated on all the day, may as well ſay that one is enough for med tation of an whole yeere. A ſecond Sermon, or the afternoones cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing in good manner, will not hinder, but further the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the forenoone. It reſtraineth alſo the people from vaine exerciſes, from drinking, and guſling, and the like.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:1764:25"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> 
               <note place="margin">Againſt Nonreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie.</note>The abuſes of this day cannot be reformed, neyther can there be ſuch preaching and catechiſing without ſuppreſſion of nonreſidencie and pluralitie of liuing. It is as truely as commonly ſaid by ſound diuines, that <hi>they that teach by Vicars and Curats, and not in their owne perſons, ſhall goe to heauen by Vicars and Curats, and not in their own perſons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">De pontif. Romano cont. 4. q 4.</note> 
               <hi>Qui vicaria opera</hi> (ſayth Doctor <hi>Whitaker</hi>) <hi>vtuntur, ij non niſi vicariorum mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem &amp; ſalutem expectare poſſunt.</hi> So ſay other diuines againſt whom no exception can be taken.<note place="margin">D. Morton Apol. part. 1. cap. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Qui per alium munere ſuo praedicandi defungitur, habebit ſalutem vicariam, ſed poenam per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonariam. Ibit ille in gehennam per ſe, in Paradiſum per alium.</hi> The ſame is to be ſayd of pluralitie of liuings: becauſe plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts cannot but be Nonreſidents, and teachers by other. Neyther is the reformation of theſe enough for the better ſanctifying of the Lords day, and for the better inſtructing of Gods people without the reformation of Miniſters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues touching their liues and conuerſation: whereby often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes they do more hurt then good by their Miniſterie, how ſound and diligent ſoeuer. And in reſpect of theſe enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of Miniſters, ſuch people as liue vnder them may well complayne as the woman of the <hi>Shunems</hi> ſonne did being ſicke vnto death, <hi>My head, my head.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kin. 4.13</note> The ſufferance of all theſe nonreſidents, pluraliſts, and ſcandalous Miniſters is a great blemiſh to our Church, and the bane of many ſoules: yea alſo, the ruine of learning; though pluralities be mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned as meanes for preferment of learning. For whiles one hath much or too much, an other hath nothing. To ſerue the cures alſo of ſuch nonreſidents and pluraliſts, many yong ſchollers not grounded in learning, are taken from the Vniuerſities, and ſo cannot ſtay till they be fit to do good in the countrye. By theſe meanes alſo the Miniſterie is brought into great contempt, whiles Nonreſidents themſelues goe for Maiſters, and their Curats be accounted but Seruants, and are ſo called. Some alſo of ſuch great Maſters make their Seruing-men Miniſters to ſerue their Cures, and account that a great reward of their good ſeruice. If any haue able Curats,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1764:26"/>and ſuch as take paynes in teaching, what iniquitie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice is it for them to ſuffer other to take ſuch paynes for a ſmall ſtipend, and themſelues liuing idly to haue all the gaines? And that ſometymes when their Curats haue a greater charge of children then themſelues? Some of theſe great Maſters alſo will not ſuffer their ſayd Curats to preach twiſe in a Lords day. The inſcription of ſome of their owne canons ſeemeth more to condemne theſe enormities, then the canons themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> Euerie able Miniſter may haue ſufficient mayntenance without ſuch pluralities.<note place="margin">Able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance without pluralities.</note> I meane ſufficient in ſober ſort without prodigalitie to maynteyne himſelfe and his charge, able notwithſtanding to keepe conuenient hoſpitalitie, and yet to leaue ſome thing to his children. Such mayntenance may be prouided by vniting diuers ſmall Churches, as eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in cities and townes, ſo ſometymes alſo in the countrie: which is the more neceſſarie, becauſe many Pariſhes haue not a conuenient auditorie. For as the Orator ſayd of an Orator. <hi>Quemadmodum tibicen ſine tibiis canere non poteſt, ita nec Oraton ſine multitudine eloquens eſſe poteſt,</hi> ſo may it be ſayd of the Miniſters of the word, that the paucitie of ſome auditories doth much diſcourage them, and coole their zeale: but full congregations do put life into them. And were not a man of good gifts better to imploy them vpon ſome good companie, then to ſpend his tyme and ſtrength vpon a few? From ſome liuings alſo that are now very great, and yet haue but a few people, ſomewhat might be detracted to the ſupply of other. Are there not many Impropriations worth 400 or 500 yea 600. <hi>li. per annum,</hi> where the Miniſter hath but 10. <hi>li.</hi> ſtipend (perhaps alſo his diet to liue in ſlauiſh manner in ſome Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans Houſe, as a Fellow to other Seruingmen) or ſome other ſmall maintenance? Ye are wiſe to whom I now ſpeak, more largely to conſider of theſe things. Moreouer, how might the Lands of Cathedrall Churches now chiefly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied for maintenance of idle Singingmen, Quireſters, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan plaiers, Canons, and pettie Canons (as they call them)
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1764:26"/>Virgerers, Doorekeepers, and ſuch like, be conuerted to the maintenance of preaching the Goſpel? The Temple of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> being defaced, wherein ſuch ſinging and Muſike was only commanded, why ſhould God now be ſerued in one place more then in another? Is he not euerie where the ſame, and in the ſame manner to be worſhiped? Why alſo may not all the Males of an whole Dioceſſes, be enioined at ſometimes euerie yeere to appeare in ſuch Cathedrall Churches as all the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were commanded at ſometimes to worſhip in the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as well as to haue God ſo to be worſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in Cathedrall Churches, and not in all other? May not the Lord well ſay,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath required this at your hands?</hi> So likewiſe to vſe the holy Scripture in this time of the Goſpel, as in ſuch chanting they are vſed, without vnderſtanding or edifying of other, Is it not a plaine abuſe of them? Were it not alſo much better for Prebends (if they ſtill enioy their places) to take paines in ſome particular Paſtorall charge (eſpecially where there is but ſmall maintenance otherwiſe) then to liue lurking idly in Cathedrall Churches? Diuers rich men alſo in diuers Corporat Townes, and elſe-where, hauing great tradings, now paying nothing, but two pence a yeere, or ſome other ſmall matter for their Eaſter offering, as alſo other that haue no Trades but liue idly of their Lands (like Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen as they ſay, but rather like loiterers) might be conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to yeeld ſome maintenance to the Miniſters <hi>that labour in the Word, and watch for their Soules.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.6. Heb. 13.17.</note> Why ſhould their poore Farmers that perhaps occupie a Farme but of ten pound a yeere, and at a deere rate, and hauing nothing elſe to liue of, and yet haue great charges, pay thirtie or fourtie ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a yeere to the Miniſters, and they that haue diuers Farmes, for which they receiue rents, pay nothing? Yea they haue the more need ſo to doe,<note place="margin">Marke 10 23.25.</note> becauſe it is harder for rich men to enter into the Kingdome of Heauen, then for other. Should not Soiourners alſo, yea and Seruants, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially hauing good wages, being partakers of the Word, communicate to him that teacheth? The Apoſtles before
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1764:27"/>mentioned generall precept in this behalfe is without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> But here leaſt any ſhould thinke me no friend to the ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient maintenance of able Miniſters, may it pleaſe you all to know me ſo farre from any ſuch thing, that I wiſh no ſuch Miniſters to haue leſſe then an hundred pound by the yeere: and alſo more, according to their gifts, to their charge, and to their former education: Some hauing been ſo brought vp from their youth and being ſo inexperienced in matters of this life: yea, ſome alſo being ſo deuoted to their Bookes, that other can better liue of an hundred pound then they of two hundred. It is alſo lamentable, that there is no better prouiſion for the Wiues and Children of godly and painfull Miniſters: whereby ſome ſeeme the more couetous, and ſome leaue nothing behind them. Sometime likewiſe a man liueth to the brinke of Harueſt, and then dying loſeth all his paines almoſt of the yeere before: the next Incumbent ceazing vpon all, and ſhewing no, or little mercie to the poore Widow and Fatherleſſe Children of his Predeceſſour. Did not the Lord prouide otherwiſe for the Wiues and Children of the Prieſts and Leuits in the time of the Law? And is it not farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe alſo in all other reformed Churches at this day?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/> For better obſeruation likewiſe of the Lords daies, that priuate perſons may the better intend the publike exerciſes of Religion,<note place="margin">Perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted not to be arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted on the Lords day.</note> were it not meet for perſons indebted pleading feare of arreſting to reſtraine them from comming to Church, and that ſometimes in truth, hauing cruell creditours, and yet being <hi>ex animo</hi> deſirous of the Word, were it not (I ſay) meet for ſuch to haue ſome ſecuritie by Law on thoſe daies, except (bewraying their Hypocriſie) they ſhall be found in ſome Inne, Tauerne, or Alehouſe in the places where they dwell?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> As diuers daies alſo heretofore called Holy daies are now altogither by Law abrogated,<note place="margin">Holy daies to be aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> ſo why may not all the reſt yet remaining be aboliſhed for the better ſanctification of the Lords day. The diuerſitie of commodities of one ſort though neuer ſo bad, doth hinder the eſtimation and ſale of the beſt
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1764:27"/>of that kind. So doe theſe Holy daies (their difference from the Lords daies by the common ſort not diſcerned) preiudice the religious obſeruation of the Lords daies themſelues. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The retaining of theſe (being at leaſt fiue and twentie euerie yeere) cannot but greatly hinder the Common wealth of the Land. For let the loſſe of the labour of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Trades men, and Labouring men of all Occupations as this Land affordeth be well conſidered, to how great a Maſſe will the whole loſſe amount. Thirdly, On ſuch daies many ſpend more riotouſly in drinking and playing then they get in two daies before or after. Fourthly, On thoſe daies how many quarrels, and other outrages, are ordinarily and yet moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly committed. Fifthly, How many Gentlemen and other great men hauing buildings or other great workes in hand, by the abſence of their Workemen on thoſe daies (in what caſe ſoeuer their buildings or other workes for the preſent are) doe ſuſtaine great dammage? Sometime alſo ſuch Workemen doe ſo miſpend the Holy daies in glouſing and drunkenneſſe, that they are not fit for labour, either the next day, or two or three after. Sixthly, Few Maſters on ſuch daies can containe their Seruants from breaking out, &amp; diſtempering themſelues ſo, that they are the worſe the whole weeke following: yea, ſometimes for their whole life after. Seuenthly, Some of the ſaid daies by publike authoritie are more ſolemnly to be kept then the Lords daies: and in reſpect of them the Lords daies with many do <hi>vileſcere.</hi> Eighthly, That time that is commonly called <hi>Chriſtide</hi> is more profaned then halfe the yeere beſides. More likewiſe in thoſe twelue daies is lauiſhly ſpent then in halfe of the yeere after. In ſome places alſo ſome poore men looſe more time and ſpend more money in gaming, then twentie times ſo many dinners and ſuppers are worth as they haue in ſuch great Houſes: When likewiſe men are in ſuch Houſes rioting, their Wiues and Children are in great want at home: yea now and then alſo in danger of their liues at their returne either by diſtemper of drinke, or by mad griefe with themſelues for that which they haue loſt. Ninthly, How many
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1764:28"/>Apparitors and Sumners on ſuch daies ſneake vp and downe, and prole here and there, ſeeking worke for themſelues, and for their maſters, by finding ſome whom they may preſent, for their worke or abſence from Church: themſelues neither on thoſe daies, nor on the Lords daies being at Church any where, but keeping their Church betwixt two Churches, and ſometimes in ſome blind and filthy Alehouſes. Many other the like abuſes and inconueniences might be alleaged of theſe daies,<note place="margin">Col. 2 16. Gal 4.10.</note> but theſe may ſerue for a taſt, God hauing aboliſhed ſome daies that himſelfe had ordained, and the Apoſtles ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found fault with obſeruation of ſuch daies, &amp;c. ſhall men thinke themſelues bound to obſerue ſuch daies as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly haue been inſtituted only by men, at leaſt of more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate zeale at the firſt, then of any ſound Iudgement? <hi>Illud eſt verius quod prius;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. cont. Mar. lib. 4. Idem de virgin. ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landis. Cyp. Ep. 63 ad Caecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</note> 
               <hi>illud prius quod ab initio. Id ab initio quod ab Apoſtolis.</hi> And againe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritati nemo praeſcribere poteſt, non ſpacium temporum, &amp;c. Dominus noſter Chriſtus veritatem ſe non conſuetudinem cognominauit, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Cyprian, Si ſolus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus audiendus eſt, non debemus attendere, quid alius ante nos faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum putauerit, ſed quid qui ante omnes eſt Chriſtus prior fecerit. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> n. hominis conſuetudinem ſequi oportet. ſed dei veritatem, &amp;c.</hi> For ſome moderate recreation of Seruants at ſome times, your moſt Honourable Court can in your wiſedomes take order, though Holy daies be diſanulled, and that although ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould be mercileſſe in that behalfe. To conclude all for the ſanctifying of this day, may it pleaſe your Honourable Court, to conſider as of many other places of Scripture. <hi>Iſai. 58.13. &amp;c.</hi> and the like:<note place="margin">Ier. 17.42. Ezek. 20.13. and 24 and 23.38. Neh. 13.15</note> ſo eſpecially of the zeale of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> in that behalfe. The greater the worke of Redemption is then the worke of the firſt Creation, the more is the Lords day, for remembrance whereof our Lord reſted from the ſaid worke, to be regarded. This further will I add, that ſome order may be taken for inſtruction of poore priſoners, both on that day, and alſo at other times: either in the Priſon where they are, or in ſome more publike place: and that in ſuch places, and at ſuch times, as where and when their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1764:28"/>preſence may be the leſſe offenſiue and noiſome to other.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/> Before I paſſe altogether from this point of Holy daies, let me I humbly beſeech you inſert ſome thing worthy your Chriſtian conſideration,<note place="margin">Lent.</note> touching the time of Lent, becauſe though it be no holier then any other time of the yeere, yet by ſome of the vulgar ſort, yea alſo by ſome of better regard it is called the Holy time of Lent. Touching this I doe not plead for the aboliſhing of it altogether touching abſtinence from Fleſh: but only I refer the conſideration of theſe things vnto your wiſedomes: Firſt, whether it were not better to be at ſome other time of the yeere when freſh Fiſh is more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, and eaſily to be had, then to be continued ſtill as it is, at ſuch time as when there is almoſt none at all?<note place="margin">Euſ. Hiſt. Eccl. lib. 5. cap. 23. So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. lib. 5. cap. 21. Sozomen. lib. 7. ca. 19</note> The rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not vnknowne to diuers Learned in your Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Court that there haue been diuers times of Lent obſerued in diuers Countreys: yea alſo, that there haue been in ſome one Countrey diuers Lents obſerued in one yeere: though for ſhorter time then ours is: yet all called by the name of <hi>Quadrageſima,</hi> but wherefore I confeſſe I know not. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I doe refer to your wiſedomes, whether it were not fit for ſome mitigation of the vſuall ſtrictneſſe thereof: and that ſome libertie might be granted for the eating of Foules (as ſome were wont to eat of Water Foules) and of Conies, and ſome greater meats, the eating whereof might not be preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to the State of the Common-wealth? Becauſe ſome not well able to purchaſe Licence to eat Fleſh are of weake bodies, not able to feed of Fiſh, neither is Fiſh wholeſome for them. Neither would this hinder the preſeruation of Calues and Lambes, but rather further the ſame: becauſe there being more libertie of other things men would be the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to forbeare them. Thirdly, euen touching this thing alſo, were it not better for ſome libertie to be giuen to ſome poore men, that cannot well bring vp their Calues, or keepe them long (eſpecially hauing but two, or three, or foure) and them that haue many to be more ſtrictly tied to the bringing vp of a certaine number euerie yeere. If it be obiected that the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1764:29"/>former ſtrict obſernation of Lent is neceſſarie for the better maintenance of the Nauie, to omit other anſwers that many of your Honourable Court can make to this obiection, may it pleaſe you to conſider whether for helpe hereof, the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Papiſts being ſuffered ſtill to liue (though their life may be our death, and mercie ſhewed to them may be crueltie to the whole Land) then foraſmuch as they attribute ſuch holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to Fiſh (as not hauing periſhed in the Flood) it were not verie fit for ſuch and other Papiſts ſo remaining, to be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all the yeere long from Fleſh and to feed only of Fiſh? I doubt not but that the reſtraint of them all the yeere from Fleſh, would be as good for maintenance of the Nauie, as the reſtraint of all ſorts, only for a time. And oh how holy would ſuch Papiſts be by this meanes? Eſpecially if alſo of their owne accord they would forbeare all Fruit, and all things made of Fruit, Figs, &amp;c. Marmalads, &amp;c. Wine, and Beere, &amp;c. as they which alſo periſhed in the Flood?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/> Moreouer, to proceed now to ſome other 0146 0436 V 2 marters, as all in Parliament are in place of Fathers to this Kingdome,<note place="margin">Choice of Parliament men to be free.</note> and as his Maieſtie in his late moſt gracious Proclamation forbad all choiſe of Knights &amp; Burgeſſes to be made of any Bankrupts, and other greatly indebted, as likewiſe of any ſuſpected not to be ſound in Religion, and as your Parliament hath alreadie taken ſome order for the preſent in ſuch things, and ye haue moſt worthily acquited your ſelues in diſmiſſing of ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully choſen by Letters, or otherwiſe, ſo all poſteritie ſhall haue cauſe to bleſſe God, for ſome certaine Law now to be made for preuenting of ſuch euils for euer hereafter: and for making all vncapable of any place in that High Court that ſhall vſe any ſuch meanes for a place.<note place="margin">None vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der age to be of the Parliament</note> Why alſo ſhould any Young men whoſe Sonnes ſoeuer be admitted into ſo great a Councell for making of Lawes for the whole Kingdome, that cannot well gouerne themſelues; and that are ſo young, as their Bils or Bonds for paiment of money are not good in Law? Is it not a Iudgement threatned by the Lord, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>be would appoint Children to be their Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>and Babes to rule
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1764:29"/>ouer them?</hi> If none be admitted into your Vpper Houſe, but ſuch as are of Age (except perhaps to ſee the order thereof, and to be the fitter for future times) why ſhould any of young yeeres be otherwiſe admitted into the Nether Houſe? The longer theſe grieuances haue hitherto been tollerated, the more high time it is now for them to be reformed. The like may be ſaid for preuenting of confuſion in Election of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, eſpecially of Knights for your moſt Honorable Houſe. This euill may eaſily be auoided, if Election be made by a kind of Scrutinie, ſome principall, wiſe, graue, and religious Knights and Gentlemen for Shieres, and other for Townes being appointed to take euerie mans voice in writing, and ſworne firſt to deale faithfully therein.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> In the former conſideration, oh that your Honourable Senat would be pleaſed to take ſome order for more libertie for publike &amp; priuate Faſts,<note place="margin">Publike and priuat Faſts.</note> as occaſion ſhall require the ſame. By Gods gracious bleſſing heretofore vpon ſuch Faſts (as in the yeere of the Earth-quake this laſt Eaſter one and fourtie yeeres: and in the yeere <hi>1588,</hi> and at other times) we may the more deſire the ſame now and hereafter. For certainly all Gods Iudgements being well conſidered, the ſecuritie of all ſorts in this behalfe, may be well thought to be the greateſt Iudgement of all other. Did not <hi>Dauid</hi> command all his people <hi>to rent their Clothes, to gird themſelues with Sack-cloth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 38.</note> 
               <hi>and to mourne for Abner, becauſe a Prince and a great man was that day fallen in Iſrael?</hi> Alas therefore that we hauing ſeene the fall of ſome of greater worth then <hi>Abner,</hi> and had many other Iudgements beſides, ſhould thinke of no ſuch thing. Nay rather, the performance of ſuch exerciſes hath been accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as pettie Treaſon. Many may meet and ſit daies and nights, eating, drinking, playing, and being drunke, and committing many outrages, and yet be in no danger, in no feare: But (woe is me that I may ſay ſo much) for ſome to meet either to faſt and pray, or to helpe one another by repetition of Sermons; or to confer only priuatly of ſuch things, as they haue heard publikely taught, &amp;c. theſe meetings are accounted and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1764:30"/>as conuenticles. What a ſtrange thing is it alſo, that all other Churches of other Nations both abroad, and here in our Kingdome, ſhould haue praiers and faſting for the Prince and Princeſſe <hi>Palatine,</hi> and yet we ſhould neglect the ſame, that in the Bond of loiall loue to his Maieſtie ſhould be moſt forward in ſuch duties? Alas alſo, that in theſe preſent great diſtreſſes and perſecutions in <hi>France,</hi> and in the troubles of almoſt all other Countreys, we ſhould neither helpe them otherwiſe nor in this kind. Oh, the Lord keepe vs, from that curſe (before ſpoken of) that the Angel of the Lord inioined againſt <hi>Meroz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.23.</note> and the Inhabitants thereof. Eſpecially the Lord keepe vs from ſuch Traitors againſt his Maieſtie, againſt his Princely Sonne, againſt the Prince and Princeſſe <hi>Palatine,</hi> and their Off-ſpring, and againſt all his Maieſties Kingdomes, as ſhall ſecretly and vnder-hand perſwade any not only to neglect this holy dutie of faſting for them, but alſo condemn the ſame altogether in theſe daies of the Goſpel, as vnlawfull, and no way tolerable, but to be ſeditious and dangerous. Doubtleſſe there are too many ſuch amongſt vs, as vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of loialtie, are moſt pernitious and peſt ferous Traitours. And ſuch are not all they only, that doe vtterly cry down and forbid faſting; and thereby that helpe from Heauen (as much as in them lyeth) that the ſaid Prince and Princeſſe <hi>Palatine</hi> need abroad (and conſequently our King and his moſt Noble Sonne alſo, and therefore likewiſe all their Kingdomes, the good of the one being the good of the other.) Such (I ſay) are not only all they, that ſo oppugne faſting, but they alſo that doe what they can to with-hold all and of man from them: neither ſo only, but that alſo be Inſtruments for ſending ouer more helpe to their Enemies,<note place="margin">Num. 33.55. Iudg. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Spinola,</hi> and other, Thornes in the ſides of the Church, that beſtur their ſtumps what they can for vp-holding the curſed Kingdome of the Romane Antichriſt, the Man of Sinne, the Child of Perdition, now drawing towards his end, and therefore gaſping, ſtriuing, and ſtrugling for life: and that with all their might oppugne the Kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus: and vnder-hand alſo the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1764:30"/>of all other Princes, aboue whom the ſaid Antichriſt exalteth himſelfe.<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.4 Pſ 118.12. Act. 9.5.</note> So they compaſſe the little Flocke of Chriſt about like Bees, not knowing for all that, that they ſhall all (<hi>Spinola</hi> and his Mates) be quenched as the Fire of Thornes: becauſe it is as hard for them as before it was for <hi>Saul</hi> to kick againſt the prickes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> Touching Fraies, Quarrels,<note place="margin">Fraies and quarrels. <hi>Preu. 14.28.</hi>
               </note> and Murders within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Land, I ſhall not need to ſay any thing for more ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie for preuenting the like, though <hi>the honour of a King conſiſt much in the multitude of the people, and by the want of people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction commeth to a Prince:</hi> becauſe his Maieſtie by publique Proclamation hath ſignified his Princely indignation againſt the ſame, ſince which we haue not heard of ſo many ſuch things as before: yet a Law being more certaine and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable then a Proclamation, it were better to make ſome more ſeuere Law againſt ſuch outrages,<note place="margin">Hoſe 6.6.</note> becauſe as <hi>mercie is better then ſacrifice;</hi> ſo crueltie, eſpecially ſheading of Innocent blood, is more odious to God, then euer was the neglect of ſuch ſacrifices. <hi>Blood touching blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſe 4.2.</note> may we not feare a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie <hi>of the Lord with the whole Land?</hi> I haue credibly heard of ſixe ſtrange Murders tried at one Summer Aſſizes at <hi>Exceter, anno 1613.</hi> Firſt, Of an Huſband poiſoning his Wife. Second, Of a Wife murdering her Huſband. Third, Of a Father killing his Sonne. Fourth, Of a Sonne killing his Father. Fifth, Of a Maſter killing his Seruant. Sixth, Of a Seruant killing his Maſter. How ſtrange alſo was that three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Murder at <hi>Halſworth</hi> in <hi>Suffolke,</hi> committed foure or fiue yeeres ſince, but diſcouered the laſt yeere? Two of the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers were executed the laſt Summer <hi>1620,</hi> and the third re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued for a longer time. As by euerie Murder God is berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of one of his principall Creatures, and the King of a Subiect; ſo alſo many times a Father looſeth his Child, the Huſband a Wife, or the Wife her Huſband, a Brother and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a Brother or Siſter: many Children their Father or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, many Friends and Neighbors, a Friend and a Neighbor, and ſomtimes the Church a good Miniſter, and the Common
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1764:31"/>wealth a good Magiſtrate, or Officer. Can there therefore be too much care for preuenting of ſuch miſchiefes? All ſuch perſons as commit the ſame doe manifeſtly bewray themſelues to haue no feare of God in them.<note place="margin">Gen. 20.11.</note> Many times alſo ſome wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Murders are cleard vnder the name, either of chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medly, or at leaſt of man-ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> All kind of bodily filthineſſe euerie where ſo much abounding,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Againſt Adulterie.</hi> Num. 25.7, 8. 1 Cor. 5.6. Heb. 12.15 16.</note> hath not your Honourable Court need to be put in mind of making a Law without further delay for puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Adulterie with death? Who of any zeale can but burne to heare, and (almoſt) to ſee as much as <hi>Phineas</hi> ſaw? If one Inceſtuous perſon, and one Fornicatour be dangerous for a whole Church, oh how much more dangerous are many? The more we profeſſe, and ſome of vs boaſt of the profeſſion of the Goſpel, and of the glorious ſtate of our Church, the more need we haue to purge our Land of ſuch euils. As death according to Gods Commandement is the puniſhment of Adulterie in moſt other Countreys, and ſo ought to be by the iudgement of moſt Diuines (none almoſt being ſo bold as to write to the contrarie) ſo why ſhould it not be in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? Our Lawes inflict death vpon ſome tranſgreſſions of the eighth Commandement, why therefore ſhould Adulterie be ſo lightly puniſhed? By the order of the Commandements and by the teſtimonie of <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6.30.</note> Adulterie plainly appeareth to be greater then Theft. If the proneneſſe of our Nation to Theft, doe require the greater puniſhment of Theft, are not the people as prone alſo to Adulterie and other carnall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe? Oh let vs take need, that as now we ſay, that no man ſhall keepe his goods in ſafetie, were not the puniſhment of Theft ſo ſeuere as it is, ſo the time come not if further ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie preuent it not, when no man ſhall keepe his Wife, or his Daughter, or Maid-ſeruant from the violence of other. The Lord that gaue the Morall Law, and appointed puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for euerie tranſgreſſion,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.3.</note> being <hi>a God of knowledge,</hi> knew before the inclination of all Nations to one ſinne as well as to another. And is not our Nation as much inclined to all
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1764:31"/>breaches of the ſeuenth Commandement, as vnto Theft? At leaſt to ſuch Theft as by our Law is puniſhable with death? Alas the poore chiefly doe offend in this kind: but all ſorts, eſpecially the greater are moſt prone to the other. Moreouer by the ſinne of Adulterie the eighth Commandement is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the higheſt degree:<note place="margin">Gen. 2.24.</note> For firſt of all the heart of a mans Wife, that is one Fleſh with her Huſband is ſtolen.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.6.</note> Is not the Wife more then any goods? Secondly, by this ſinne the whole ſtate, and the name it ſelfe of a man, yea ſometimes of Noble Houſes, is deriued to another, euen of moſt baſe ſtate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. Thirdly, Are not many Noble Houſes and Families rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated thereby?<note place="margin">Gen. 34.2 19.</note> The example of <hi>Schechem</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor,</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe doe teſtifie theſe things. <hi>Hamor was a chiefe Ruler, and the Lord of the Countrey where he dwelt.</hi> And of what King were there euer ſo great things ſpoken as of <hi>Salomon?</hi> Yet the Fornication of <hi>Schechem</hi> was the ruine of all the <hi>Schechemites:</hi> and the loue of many Wiues by <hi>Salomon</hi> was the deſolation of his Kingdome in his Sonnes daies.<note place="margin">1 Kin. 11.1 11.30, 31.</note> How many troubles alſo followed <hi>Dauids</hi> one Adulterie with <hi>Bathſheba?</hi> Euen to the endangering of the loſſe of his life and whole Kingdome?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> The Law alreadie made for death (as in caſe of Felonie) of any man that ſhall haue two Wiues liuing togither, may the more perſwade your Honourable Court to take order for death againſt Adulterie: becauſe the time was when Polyga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie was for many yeeres togither accounted lawfull: though from the firſt inſtitution of Mariage, it neuer was ſo indeed: as appeareth by the teſtimonie of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.13.</note> and by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the firſt inſtitution of Mariage by our Sauiour himſelfe.<note place="margin">Mat. 19.4. Mark. 10.5.</note> It doth the more alſo concerne your moſt Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Court to haue regard hereof for the better preſeruing of your owne poſteritie from this ſinne, that ſo their Names, Lands, and Inheritances may deſcend to them, to whom of moſt right the ſame appertaine. Shall any feare that if this motion ſhould take place, then themſelves or theirs ſhall firſt feele the ſmart thereof? <hi>Abſit.</hi> What hope then can there
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1764:32"/>be of the reſtraint of this ſinne hereafter? Euerie Generation to come may be feared to be more adulterous then other. Such feare alſo ſeeming to come from a guiltie conſcience, is nothing elſe but the fruit of the former lenitie towards this ſinne. Had this ſeueritie been before enacted, men would neuer haue been ſo hardned in this ſinne, as to feare the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of this Law. I will not here be ſo vncharitable, as to thinke any man will obiect the former danger of alienation of Names and Inheritances may be auoided by hauing chaſt Wiues for the nights, though they haue their Miſtreſſes on whom to ſatiſfie their luſts at other time. This were a deuilliſh ſpeech. And they that are vnchaſt themſelues may feare that which <hi>Iob</hi> wiſhed might befall to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Iob 31.9.10.</note> if at any time he had offended in this kind. <hi>Iob</hi> at that time by the courſe of Nature was not paſt the danger of that ſinne: in as much as long after <hi>he begat Sonnes and Daughters.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 42.13.</note> Neither ſpake he that for the time only preſent, but alſo to teſtifie his innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for the time paſt. Doth not the Lord alſo in Iuſtice giue an incontinent Wife, to ſuch an incontinent Huſband? Yea, doth he not alſo for the like ſinne of the Huſband, take away his grace from the Wife giuing her ouer to incontinencie, in reuenge of the incontinencie of the Huſband? Yea, doth he not ſometimes ſuffer chaſt Wines to be againſt their wills de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed by other for the ſinne in that kind by the Huſband? The example of <hi>Dauid</hi> doth plentifully teſtifie the truth hereof. That our Sauiour condemned not the Woman taken in Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie doth nothing preiudice my former plea.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12.11, 12. compared with 16.22 Iohn 8.11 Luk. 12.14</note> Firſt, Becauſe Chriſt was no Iudge in ſuch cauſes. Secondly, Becauſe if he had been a Iudge, yet her accuſers whiles he ſtooped downe, and wrot on the ground hauing all forſaken her, he could not haue proceeded againſt her.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4 5.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> alſo commanded not death to be inflicted on the inceſtuous perſon, as becauſe himſelfe was no ciuill Magiſtrate, ſo alſo becauſe the Church it ſelfe had then no ciuill iuriſdiction amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> That which hath beene moued touching Adulterie is alſo to be wiſhed againſt common Harlots that haue Baſtard after
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1764:32"/>Baſtard: ſo likewiſe againſt men ſinning in the ſame kind.<note place="margin">Againſt common Harlots</note> By the preſent impunitie, ſome haue had three, ſome foure, ſome fiue, ſome ſixe or ſeuen, and that by ſeuerall men or boies. The like may be ſaid of diuers men by their ſeruants or other filthy queanes, and yet ſtill ſuch perſons continue in their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe, as they haue any opportunitie to act the ſame: The common pennance they ſet not a ruſh by, but rather make a May-game of it: neither is it haſtily inioyned, where there is no money to diſcharge the Courts. Standing in a white ſheet they thinke as good an ornament for them, as the Surplice is for the Miniſter. They no whit feare Excommunication, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had rather be out of the Church then in it: as alſo becauſe they ſee the ſame not only executed for euerie trifle, but alſo ſometime againſt the beſt diſpoſed people; euen for righteouſneſſe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 9.22.34 Ioh. 16.2. Iudg. 19.30</note> as it was by the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſecs</hi> in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours time: and as our Sauiour foretelleth it ſhould be after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. Of theſe things I doe moſt humbly beſeech your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Court to <hi>conſider, conſult, and giue ſentence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> 
               <note place="margin">Againſt drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>Againſt drunkenneſſe more ſeueritie is yet neceſſarie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth daily increaſe, and more and more aboundeth: and is the verie chiefe and principall <hi>Foines</hi> of the former beaſtlineſſe. In drunkenneſſe alſo men may fall into the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt kind of vncleanneſſe, and neuer diſcerne the ſame, and be readie to ſwear they neuer did any ſuch thing.<note place="margin">Gen. 19.33. &amp;c. 2 Pet. 2.7</note> This is moſt euident by the example of <hi>Lot,</hi> though otherwiſe a iuſt man. Yea, what ſinne is there, either before named or other, that commeth not out of this ſinke? This ſinne maketh a man a beaſt for the time, and yet for a man to be made a beaſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded for one of the moſt remarkable Iudgements that euer were. Yea,<note place="margin">Dan 4.33.</note> the Drunkard in his mad drunkenneſſe is worſe then euer was <hi>Nebuchadnezzer</hi> in his beaſtly condition. For all the while he ſo continued we neuer read that he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any other ſinnes.<note place="margin">Rom. 3.14 Pſal. 73.9. Pſal. 12.4.</note> But the <hi>mouth of the Drunkard is full of eurſing and bitterneſſe. They ſet their mouth againſt Heauen, and their tongue walketh through the earth. They</hi> eſpecially <hi>ſay, with our tongues will we preuaile, our lips are our owne, who is Lord ouer vs.</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:1764:33"/>As it is ſaid of an Orator, <hi>Ex eius ore verba magno impetu at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aeſtu erumpebant, non ſecus ac ſeruentes aquae ebulliunt &amp; exiliunt,</hi> ſo may it be ſaid of him that is giuen to drinke, whiles drike is in him, and he in drinke, <hi>Ex eius ore nefanda omnis generis iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramenta, blaſphemiae, imprecationes, conuitia, maledicta, ſtultiloqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, turpiloquium, obſcaeni ſermones, &amp; eius farinae reliqua omnia mala, non ſecus ac feruentes aquae ebulliunt &amp; exiliunt.</hi> It is ſaid by one, <hi>The proud man hath no God, the ennious man hath no Neighbour, the angry man hath not himſelfe;</hi> but the drunkard may truly be ſaid,<note place="margin">Deu. 21.21</note> not to be himſelfe. For drunkenneſſe natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Parents muſt bring forth their owne Sonne that will not be reclaimed from it, to the Magiſtrate to be ſtoned to death by all the people of the place where ſuch an one dwelleth. I could diſcourſe of <hi>Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.37, 38.</note> becomming vpon report made by <hi>Abigail</hi> of dangers like to haue befallen him,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.28.</note> but yet eſcaped, becomming (I ſay) like a ſtone, and fearfully dying: of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, Dauids</hi> Sonne, in drunkenneſſe being murdered: of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hadad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 20 16.</note> and two and thirtie Kings with him in their drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſubdued by the <hi>Jſraelites:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 16.9 10.</note> of <hi>Elah</hi> before that in his drunkenneſſe ſlaine by his Seruant <hi>Zimri:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.30, 31.</note> of <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> the ſame night after his drinking and glouſing looſing both life and Kingdome. But to omit all theſe the <hi>Magdeburgenſes</hi> in their <hi>Centuries,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Centur. 11 cap. 6. pag. 346.</note> record out of our owne Hiſtories, that our own Nation hauing ſpent all a night in drunkenneſſe was the verie next day ouercome by the <hi>Normans.</hi> What ſhall I ſay more?<note place="margin">Hoſe 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>Whordome and Wine, and new Wine, take away the heart,</hi> ſo ſtupifying and brawning the ſame, that no threatnings, or execution of Iudgements, neither any exhortations to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance will pierce it, or at leaſt preuaile againſt it. All theſe things cry in the eares of the Lord of Hoſt, and I hope will ſo cry in your Chriſtian cares, that they will be heard and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt this fowle Monſter. Yea, ſo preuaile, that as <hi>Amnon hated Thamar with a greater hatred then euer his loue had beene wherewith he loued her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.15.</note> and commanded his Seruant <hi>to ſhut her out,</hi> and to locke or bolt <hi>the dore vpon her,</hi> that ſhe might not return, ſo ſuch order ſhall now be taken againſt this ſinne,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1764:33"/>that all men ſhall hate it more, then euer they loued it, and ſo ſhut the doore of this whole kingdome vpon it, that it ſhall neuer preuaile as it hath done. I preſcribe no particular pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: but leaue it altogeather to your wiſedomes. Onely I wiſh ſome order to be taken who ſhall be puniſhed for a drunkard: and that for as much as rich men care not for fiue ſhillings (though they will hardly giue two pence to a poore man) and yet will be drunke as well as other, that therefore ſome greater matter be enacted.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> Neither are other exceſſiue drinkings altogeather to be neglected,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue drinkings.</hi> 1. Pet. 4.3. Iſai. 5.11.</note> the Apoſtle hauing not only diſtinguiſhed drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes from drinkings, but alſo reckoned the one and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſinnes of the heathen: and the Prophet hauing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced a wo as wel to that as to drunkennes it ſelfe: &amp; that heathen Emperor <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> in his Roiall and magn ficent feaſt of 180. daies hauing left ſo noble a preſident againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderat drinking, and of all ſo brietie in drinking, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>all their drinking ſhould be in order, and none might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</hi> Oh how doth this condemne many feaſtmakers among Chriſtians, that thinke it their glorie, or honour, or worſhip, to vrge men to drinke vnto drunkenneſſe? This is ſo foule a thing that in the moſt corrupt age of the Church, a Councel held at <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe <hi>anno 1215.</hi> in which were Ambaſſadors or Orators at <hi>Rome,</hi> from <hi>Conſtantinople, France, England, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie, Ieruſalem, Cyprus,</hi> and <hi>Arrogan</hi> with <hi>412</hi> Biſhops, and Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots and Priors aboue <hi>800.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Centur. 13. cap. 13 p. 806.</note> and in all of Prelats about <hi>1315.</hi> the Pope himſelfe ſitting for <hi>Preſident,</hi> euen this <hi>Councell</hi> (I ſay) <hi>Can. 15.</hi> after ſentence againſt drunkenneſſe in the Clergie, ſaith <hi>vnde illum abuſum decernimus penitus eſſe abolendum, &amp;c. Wherefore we decree that abuſe to be altogeather aboliſhed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in certaine quarters the drinkers doe binde themſelues to drinke equall portions, and he by the iudgement of ſuch drinkers is moſt commended, that maketh moſt drunke, and that draweth dry the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt cups.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 940.</note> The like <hi>Canon</hi> is afterward by a Councell of <hi>Colon</hi> againſt the ſame abuſe. Such drinking is called drinking of health, and it is accounted a great indignitie therefore not to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1764:34"/>pledge one drinking to the health of his Maieſtie: but alas, it is no health, either to ſoule or body: but ſickneſſe &amp; death to both: to plead a ſecret comprecation of health in ſuch drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is an abomination to God, <hi>inter plena pocula</hi> to mix com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations. Such drinkers alſo doe ſeldome or neuer pray (at feaſt as they ought) either for the health of them to whom they doe ſo drinke, or for their owne health. We are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to pray for the health of other, but neuer to drinke. Some of the antient Fathers haue greatly condemned drinking to the health of the Emperour, and haue highly commended praying in that behalfe. What health can there be for ſoule or bodie, when ſome in ſuch drinking haue fallen downe ſtarke dead? Sometime alſo ſuch drinkers drinke themſelues in time out of all bodily faſhion, out of money, out of wit, out of grace: hauing no more money in their purſes, no more wit in their heads, no more grace in their hearts then they leaue wine, ale, or beere in their cups, when they haue drunke <hi>ad imum,</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bottomes of ſuch cups, and the heeles of themſelues vpward. O the commonneſſe of this ſinne in theſe daies, not only in baſe places, but in many great houſes: yea ſometimes in the houſes of religious great perſons: where ſeruants thinke it a diſgrace to themſelues, and a diſcurteſie to other great mens ſeruants, if they drinke them not drunke: yea ſo drunke that they can doe no ſeruice to their maſters homeward: yea, it were well if ſome great perſons themſelues, yea very great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did not glorie in this which for all that is their great ſhame. In common Schooles Potations are but once a yeare: in Lent: and in the afternoones: but theſe wretches, theſe ſots make their Potations euery moneth, euery weeke, euery day as ſoone as they are out of their beds, in the forenoones, as well as in the afternoones euen in the night till they be ſo oppreſt with drinke that they be forced <hi>edormire crapulam.</hi> Is it not therefore high time to repreſſe this euill? More then time. If reformation hereof begin in the houſes of Nobles, Knights, and Gentlemen, as alſo of the moſt dignified Prelates, it will be the more eaſily enlarged further. For how can miniſterie or
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1764:34"/>magiſtracie be well executed,<note place="margin">Iſai. 28.7. Leuit. 10.9 1. Tim. 3.3. Tit. 1.7. Pro. 31.4. Iſai. 5.25. 1. Maccab. 16.15.</note> by them that are culpable in this kinde? Examples of Magiſtrates ye haue ſeene before. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prelates &amp;c. That of Simon the Prieſt with his two ſons <hi>Mattathia</hi> and <hi>Iuda</hi> (though it be <hi>Apocrypha</hi>) is not altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be deſpiſed. For they all three hauing drunke largely by the policie of <hi>Ptolomaeus</hi> the ſon of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ubuſh,</hi> were ſlaine by the ſaid <hi>Ptolomaeus.</hi> Now here alſo is to be conſidered the foule abuſe of <hi>Tobacco.</hi> I call it abuſe, becauſe it may be that for Phyſike there is ſome vſe of it: but <hi>Quorum non est vſus eorum non est abuſus.</hi> And this abuſe is euen in the <hi>Vniuerſities</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: yea in all other places. Euen ſuch is the abuſe hereof, that thereby more ſmoke commeth out of ſome mens noſes then out of many chimnies of ſome great houſes: euen of ſuch men as doe moſt abuſe the ſaid <hi>Tobacco.</hi> Hereby alſo the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins of drunkennſſe and exceſſiue drinkings are the more nouriſhed. Finally hereby, though many chimnies are cleane ſwept, yet the bodies of ſome men deceaſſed being opened haue beene found as foule and blacke, as chimnies are by much ſoot.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> For the better repreſſing of the former drukenneſſe and drinkings, may it pleaſe you to conſider of leſſening the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Innes,<note place="margin">Againſt multitude of Innes Tauernes and Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes.</note> Tauernes, and Alehouſes in all places. Yea, for making ſome Act for the ſtinting of the number of them in euery Parriſh of euery Towne, and in euery Village of the country; and that the number ſo ſtinted may not be increaſed afterward by any whoſoeuer. Yea alſo that none be authorized to keepe Inne, Tauerne, or Alehouſe, but ſuch as are of good fame and name for their owne ſober carriage and behauiour. As likewiſe ſufficient to vndergoe the penaltie by you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in caſe they ſhall offend by ſuffering any diſorder in their houſes contrarie to Law. But becauſe ye haue alreadie begun to take ſome order in that behalfe, I ſhall not neede to ſpeake much. Notwithſtanding there is the more neede to be had for the leſſening of the number of them in all places, and for reformation of the great reſort vnto them, eſpecially by ſuch as haue houſes of their owne in the ſame Parriſhes:
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1764:35"/>and chiefly of the great abuſes in them by the former ſinnes of drunkenneſſe and exceſſiue drinkings, by playing at vnlawful games, by ſwearing, by ſinging filthy ſongs, and by many other the like diſorders. In reſpect of all theſe there is the more care to be had for redreſſe of the premiſes: becauſe ſuch hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are the chiefe bane of many mens children, the ſpoyle of many Seruants: the ruine of many yong Heyres; the meanes of much whoredome, and of many quarrelings and murders: the harbors of many Theeues to contriue their Robberies: and the places whither to bring their theſe ſtollen goods: and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally the boothes of all other iniquities. Some of them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by ſome Iuſtices, yea at quarter Seſſions for a time are repreſt; but how ſoone after be they erected againe? Such Alehouſes alſo are moſt dangerous, that are in blinde corners, farre remote from other houſes: ſo alſo ſuch as are the more needles, becauſe they are neere, to Market Townes that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound with them: and both theſe are the more dangerous, becauſe Conſtables and other neighbours canot daily ſee the behauiours in them: the one to informe the other to reforme whatſoeuer is amiſſe: yea, alſo touching all Alehouſes, Innes, and Tauernes, for the better repreſſing of them, and redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all abuſes in them, it is to be wiſhed that no knowen riotous perſons, and ſuch as are giuen to play, and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſpecially men ſeruants, and ſons of parents knowne, might be ſuffered to runne vpon the ſcore, and to take more then they preſently pay for and that therefore all ſuch ale or beere ſellers, Innekeepers, or Tauerners as ſhould ſuffer any ſuch Seruants or mens ſonnes, of age or vnder age ſo to doe, ſhould haue no benefit of Law for recouerie of any ſuch wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full debts. Finally, may it pleaſe you to conſider how conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient it were for all Tauerners, Innekeepers, Vinteners, Brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and the like in all Cities and Townes corporate to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from bearing any chiefe magiſtracie in any ſuch places My reaſon of this ſhort motion I leaue to your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable wiſedomes to conceiue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> Touching playes and players, the oftener, and by the more
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1764:35"/>Lawes ſtill in force they haue beene condemned,<note place="margin">Play, and Players.</note> the more I hope ye will now this once more ſo ſtrike and wound them, that Cities, Townes, and Villages ſhall neuer hereafter be ſo troubled and robbed by them, as hitherto they haue beene, and yet yeerely are, notwithſtanding all former Lawes againſt them: the rather becauſe of that intollerable inſolencie of them that before hath beene touched, euen againſt the greateſt States in the Land, as alſo againſt worthy Preachers of the Word in ſuch places, as where they haue beene ſuffered to play. And who doe moſt reſort to ſuch companions, but their like (for the moſt part) in all profaneneſſe? The pooreſt alſo, and moſt beggerly perſons will ſpare a pennie or two to ſee and heare their foule ſports, that haue not ſo much more in their purſes, to buy neceſſarie food for their Families: yea, ſuch for the moſt part doe moſt eagerly reſort to ſuch exerciſes, as neuer care for any exerciſes of Religion priuate or publike.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> Bankrupts, Ingrocers of Commodities, and all Cozoners of men, eſppecially in great things,<note place="margin">Bankrupts, &amp;c.</note> haue the more need of your ſeuere animaduerſion, becauſe by ſuch many are vndone, and themſelues pretending decay grow rich: and when they haue compounded with their creditors for the third, or fourth, or eighth part ſometime of their debt, they haue enough left for themſelues and for their Children afterward. This is much greater robberie, then (without Murder) to take Purſes by the high-way. Theſe vermin are the more dangerous, becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times when they are neereſt breaking, &amp; intend to breake, then to deceiue men the more, they make the greateſt ſhew of wealth, by building, by coſtly apparrel, by feaſting, &amp; the like. With theſe may be ioyned thoſe that vpon their ſecond<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges make Ioynters to their ſecond Wiues, hauing before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaied their ſtates to their Children by their firſt Wiues. So likewiſe they that ſell annuities out of their Lands, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue ſecretly conuaied. Againſt ingrocing of Farmes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ingrocers.</hi> Prou. 23.4.</note> I hope theſe laſt yeeres, haue made men to <hi>ceaſe</hi> (as <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:1764:36"/>ſpeaketh in like caſe) <hi>from their ſuch wiſedome:</hi> and taught them that haue many to deſire to be rid of them: yea,<note place="margin">Land-lords to abate rents.</note> I hope alſo that theſe yeeres of plentie will teach great perſons that are Lords of many Farmes, to mittigate their rents of their own accord, without any further order to conſtrain them ſo to do, leſt if they doe not, their Farmers run away, leauing them and their Lands in the lurch: to their as great loſſe as before they had gaine by their hard rents: in the hardneſſe of their hearts looking for their rents, but neuer caring with what difficulty, and griefe of heart their Farmers labour to maintaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their Families:<note place="margin">Pſ. 127.2.</note> 
               <hi>riſing early, and ſitting vp late, and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bread of ſorrowes,</hi> while their Land-lords liue in eaſe and pleaſures. Notwithſtanding the woe of ſuch Land-lords will be greater in the end, then the preſent griefe of their poore Tenants.<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.15. Pſal. 14.5. Amos 8.6, 7. Amos 4.2.</note> For <hi>they beat the Lords people to peices, &amp; grind the faces of the poore: and eat them vp as men eat bread:</hi> yea, <hi>they ſallow them vp, and buy them for ſiluer: and ſell them for ſhooes.</hi> Will the Lord alwaies beare this? No, no: <hi>He hath ſworne by the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of Iacob, that certainly he will neuer forget ſuch workes, &amp; by his owne holineſſe, that the dayes ſhall come vpon ſuch when he will take them away with hookes:</hi> that is, he will deſtroy them ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly, and vnawares, as the Fiſh is taken with the hooke (Will the Lord be forſworne?) Yea, he threatneth further, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſuch great ones <hi>build houſes of hewen ſtones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 5.11</note> 
               <hi>they ſhall not dwell in them: and though</hi> alſo <hi>they plant pleaſant <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyards, they ſhall not drinke Wine of them.</hi> Yea further which is heauieſt of all,<note place="margin">Amos 8.7.</note> the Lord threatneth <hi>neuer to forget them: and to bring ſuch a plague vpon them, as out of the which they ſhall neuer plucke their necke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 2.3. Mich. 3.4.</note> and that although they cry <hi>vnto the Lord, yet he will not heare them.</hi> Will the Lord deale thus with them that oppreſſe the bodies of men? Oh then, how will he deale with them that are cruell to mens Soules? Becauſe alſo ſome Executors of laſt Wills &amp; Teſtaments of the dead are as great oppreſſors as the former by waſting Orphans goods in ſuit of Law (ſometime againſt ſuch as to whom in nature they are moſt
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1764:36"/>bound) in building, purehaſing of Lands in their own names, and in ſo renuing of Leaſes, left to their truſt for ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans, and in liuing riotouſly, &amp; other like waies, ſo that ſuch Orphans comming to age, are fruſtrated of that which their Parents left them, may it pleaſe you to conſider of doing ſome thing, according to your godly wiſedomes for preuenting hereafter of this great euill: the father becauſe Executors may die, and often doe die, before ſuch Orphans be of age. The ſame I wiſh concerning ſome that haue ingroced ſome ſums of mony into their hands, &amp; therewith purchaſed Lands, and then moſt wickedly laid violent hands vpon themſelues, to leaue the ſaid land to their heires, becauſe lands pay no debts. Such I haue known, and therefore I do the rather commend the ſame to your Honourable Court, to be preuented for the time to come. Touching oppreſſion by Eccleſiaſticall Courts, in taking greater fees for probat of Wills, Letters of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, for Excommunications, and Abſolutions, for Citati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; appearances according to ſuch Citations (iuſt or vniuſt) inforcing alſo men to buy their Bookes of Articles, &amp; to pay ten or twelue pence for a Book of them (deere of two pence) and other ſuch waies: as ye haue begun a little to pry into them, ſo hoping ye will ſift ſuch things further, I will ſpare all further ſpeech of them: as alſo of the extortion of ſome Biſhops themſelues in taking much more then they ought for Letters of Orders, for Inſtitution, Induction, and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> Notwithſtanding, I haue need here to ad ſomething touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Symonie and giuing of money or moneys worth,<note place="margin">Againſt Symonie.</note> by any Miniſters themſelues, or by any their friends in their behalfe, for Benefices or any other Eccleſiaſticall preferments, to ſuch as doe more loue to ſee money then to ſee God:<note place="margin">Exod. 23.8 Dan. 16.19</note> and that by ſuch ſeeing of money haue their eyes ſo blinded, and their words ſo peruerted (though before they ſeemed righteous) that they can neither ſee that that is right, nor (like a drunken man) ſpeake a right word. This is the more worthy your
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1764:37"/>wiſe conſideration, becauſe although the Lawes alreadie againſt the ſaid corruption enacted be ſo ſtrickt, that a man would wonder how that foule and monſtrous ſinne ſhould be ſtill continued, yet ſuch is the wicked wit of man, that it hath wayes and wiles enough to elude all alreadie done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: and ſo to beguile their owne Soules, that Symonie to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Patrons, or to their Wiues, or to their Children, or to their Seruants, or to their Friends, is ſtill as common, as rife, as vſuall, as if there were no Law at all againſt it. And albeit a man would thinke that no more ſeueritie could be deuiſed to repreſſe the ſame, yet if ye ſhall be pleaſed to entertaine this further motion, I doubt not but that your wiſedomes will finde out ſomewhat more then yet hath beene for the curbing and reſtraining, both giuer and taker for the time to come from all ſuch corruption. The ſame I doe likewiſe commend to your wiſedomes for reſtraint of the like euill in the collating of Academicall preferments, eſpecially Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerſhips and Fellowſhips in the Vniuerſities. For it is lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and verie lamentable, to ſee the great change of thoſe places, as in other things ſo alſo in this, from that they were fourtie or fiftie yeeres paſt, when there was no ſuch corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion almoſt knowne. It may be ſome were choſen of fauour, or by friendſhip, and Letters of great perſons that were not ſo worthy as ſome other that were paſt ouer: but as for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney corruption it was not ſo much as talked of. Afterward alſo, for reſignation of a Fellowſhip it may be the Reſigner had ſome twentie Nobles, or ten pound at the moſt. But now alas it is come to that paſſe that Maſters of Houſes take ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times fourtie pound, ſometimes fiftie pound, ſometimes an hundred Markes, ſometimes an hundred pounds, and more alſo for a poore Fellowſhip, to the great preiudice of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the hindrance of the Poore, the diſgrace of the Goſpel, and to ſuch ſhame and reproch of ſuch takers themſelues, that Libels are caſt out againſt them for the ſame. If ſome Maſters and late made Fellowes were vpon their Oathes
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1764:37"/>hereof examined, they could not if they haue any feare of God, or any conſcience denie it. Neither (I am perſwaded) would they, being eſpecially aſſured of pardon for their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence paſt in that kind. But for the time to come, were it not fit that all ſuch takers and giuers, as alſo all friends that ſhall giue any thing for any in ſuch reſpect, ſhould be ſeuerely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by your wiſedomes: as likewiſe that all that could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect ſuch dealing, ſhould be well rewarded?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> Moreouer, becauſe he that loueth paſtime, ſhall be a poore man, and he that loueth Wine and Oyle ſhall not be rich,<note place="margin">Againſt riotous ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and vnlawfull paſtimes.</note> Oh that ye would be pleaſed to take ſome order againſt ſuch things as <hi>Salomon</hi> there meaneth. I meane againſt all riot in gaming, in lauiſh and coſtly fare, in rich and curious apparell, beyond abilitie, aboue calling, not beſeeming their ſexe, whereby alſo is to be vnderſtood all exceſſe in Hunting,<note place="margin">Pro. 21.17</note> Hawking, and the like. The which exerciſes are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues lawfull, but not conuenient for all ſorts of perſons: yea ſometimes, they be made vnlawfull being immoderately vſed. And by theſe things how quickly doe many waſte their whole ſtates, <hi>and bring themſelues to be hired out for bread?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.5</note> Yea ſuch as were borne to great Inheritances. In ſome Countries I haue heard, young men prodigally giuen to be confined for their expenſes. Why may it not be ſo with vs?<note place="margin">Prodigall perſons to be confined to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes.</note> Why alſo ſhould there not a Law be made for all great men no longer to enioy their Titles and Dignities, then whiles they haue meanes to maintaine the ſame? As also for ſome in euerie Countrey to be appointed to haue power for a time, euerie yeere, or euerie two or three yeeres to call Noble mens heires and other great perſons to account after they be of age, and to examine them of their expenſes: and then vpon finding them lauiſh, Chriſtianly to admoniſh them: finding them fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall to encourage them: and if they ſhall not regard the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or third admonition, ſuch to be degraded of their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and depriued of their other priuiledges, which before they held by their places. If alſo ſome antient Ciuill Lawes
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1764:38"/>were reuiued for recouerie of money loſt by any vnder age, and that for fiftie yeeres after; or for the beſtowing of ſuch money loſt after age vpon the poore (the winners thereof being forced to make reſtitution to the Magiſtrates) that ſo the looſers may be looſers, and the winners no gainers: If ſuch Lawes (I ſay) were reuiued, what a goodly reſtraint would they make of riotous gaming? In a little Booke alſo <hi>De Moribus Turcorum,</hi> with a Preface of <hi>Luther</hi> prefixed thereto, I read, that ſuch as loſt money by play, being found were puniſhed with many ignominies. I could alledge many teſtimonies out of <hi>Iuſtinian, Peter Martyr, Caluin, Baſtingius,</hi> and diuers of the Fathers and Councels, as alſo of Heathen men, <hi>Tully,</hi> and other againſt playing and waſting of mens ſtates by playing. But I doubt not but that ſome of your Honourable Senate, can ſpeake more then my ſelfe can in this Theame, or then is fit for me to write. That that I haue written herein, I haue written without curioſitie, or any pride in medling with greater matters then belong vnto me, but onely in regard of the good of the Common-wealth, and in loue to ſuch as I ſee by ſuch meanes vainly to conſume their Patrimonie, to their owne and their Childrens miſerie, and to the ruine of their Noble or Worſhipfull Houſes. All alſo that I write I doe humbly ſubmit to your Honourable wiſedomes,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> The exceſſe of Apparell is ſuch that it hindreth Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeping,<note place="margin">Exceſſe of apparell.</note> and all good duties beſides to God and men: and thereby ſufficiently ſpeaketh againſt it ſelfe. Neither is to be condemned in thoſe reſpects for the coſtlineſſe only thereof: but alſo for the ſtrange and variable faſhions euerie yeere changed, no man or woman almoſt knowing how they may goe.<note place="margin">Iſa. 3 16. &amp;c. Zeph. 1.8. 2 Kings 9.30.</note> Doth not the Lord threaten ſeuerely to puniſh ſuch things, by whomſoeuer vſed? Or were his ſuch threatnings onely for thoſe times? The Scripture recordeth <hi>Iezabel</hi> for a Monſter of that Age. But theſe times cry downe her pride, and commend her to haue been ſober and modeſt. Touching
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1764:38"/>our late new-found Monſters, I meane Women that haue cleane cut off their Haire, and gone like Boyes or Young-men (it may be that they might be ſo taken as Pope <hi>Ioane</hi> was) as his Maieſtie hath let ſome of them ſee his frowning coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and heare his words of Princely indignation againſt them, whereby that foule faſhion was a while repreſſed, ſo I haue wiſhed his Maieſtie would likewiſe haue been pleaſed, to haue committed them to Bridewell or Bedlem, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them there to haue beene kept till their Haire were fully growne againe,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.15.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> commanded his Ambaſſadours abuſed by <hi>Hanun</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Ammon</hi> by ſhauing of halfe their Beards, <hi>to tarrie at Iericho till there beards were growne,</hi> becauſe they were aſhamed. Were not this ſo much the more iuſt, becauſe theſe impudent Women ſin againſt the light of Nature, and yet are not aſhamed, but glorie in their ſhame? Yea both ſuch Women, and alſo men offending in the contrarie by wearing Woman-like long Haire, doe giue <hi>Paule</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt the lye in ſo doing.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.14.15.</note> For <hi>Paule</hi> by the Holy Ghoſt hath ſaid, <hi>Doth not nature it ſelfe teach you, that for a man to haue long haire it is a ſhame? But for a woman to haue long haire it is a glorie to her.</hi> Doe not therefore ſuch men, and ſuch women ſay nay to all that, and ſpeake the cleane contrarie, <hi>viz. That it is verie comely for men to weare long haire, and a great ornament for women to cut off their haire, and to become Tomboyes?</hi> Oh how doe theſe cry to men for reformation, and without reformation to God for Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> Here alſo I may briefely inſert ſome thing againſt the multiplicitie of Faires: eſpecially in ſmall Villages,<note place="margin">Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie of Faires.</note> and pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Parriſhes: as the which are onely meanes to maintaine Rogues and Vagabonds, and ſuch drunkenneſſe and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as whereof before I haue ſpoken: and whereby like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, there is much more detriment to the Common-wealth, then any benefit. Yea alas, how is God diſhonoured many wayes by occaſion of ſuch Faires? Yea alſo, how well may
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1764:39"/>moſt Faires in great Townes be ſpared: except only ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Faires, as <hi>Bartholmew</hi> Faire at <hi>London, Sturbridge</hi> Faire by <hi>Cambridge, Lyn</hi> Mart, and the like: and excepted likewiſe great Cattell Faires in diuers Countries? Other Faires for the moſt part are more preiudiciall to Trades men in ſuch great Townes, then beneficiall to any, but only to Alehouſe-keepers, Inholders, and Tauerners.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/> May it alſo pleaſe you to conſider of ſome meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine great men from lying ſo much in <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to keep houſe in the Countrey.</hi> Rom. 12.12. Hebr. 13.2 1 Pet. 4.9. Gen. 18.3. and 19.2. Iob 31.17. Neh. 5.17.18.</note> and other Cities and Townes from their chiefe Manſion Houſes in the Countrey, as they doe, and to enioyne them to keepe Houſe in the Countrey, Hoſpitalitie being both often commanded, and alſo commended by many worthy examples of <hi>Abraham,</hi> of <hi>Lot,</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> of <hi>Nehemiah.</hi> Is it not the more neceſſarie in theſe daies for the more refreſhing of the poore, all Trades being now ſo dead as they are, and many men not knowing almoſt how to line? Yea in the ſame reſpect it is likewiſe the more needfull, by Iuſtice the better to keepe men in order, and from vſing vnlawfull ſhifts for helping of themſelues. Yea, at all times it is needfull for repreſſing of ſinnes, by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of ſuch great men, meaner Iuſtices not being of ſuch ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count as the greater. The old excuſe of the great price of things hindring Houſe-keeping in the Countrey hath lately beene remoued by the great plentie of the late yeeres, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for ſuch great perſons more eaſie Houſe-keeping. Before alſo it might haue beene the more eaſed by the more modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of expences in building, gaming, apparell, and other rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. By this meanes alſo euerie other Gentlemans burthen would be the leſſe. As many hands make quick worke, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhoulders make light burthens.<note place="margin">Exod. 18.17. &amp;c.</note> Hereby likewiſe loue would be greatly encreaſed, and the hearts of the Common people gained to loue &amp; honor ſuch great perſons the more; and be the readier for any good ſeruice of the Countrey. If ſuch likewiſe would ſo wiſely and religiouſly gouerne their houſes, that it might be ſaid of them as it was ſaid of <hi>Cornelius,</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:1764:39"/>that <hi>they feared God and all their houſholds with them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 10.2</note> Oh what light of life and godlineſſe would it giue to other? Finally, this motion is the more reaſonable, becauſe commonly ſuch great perſons chiefe Lands lye where their chiefe Houſes are: there alſo they haue the more ſeruices performed to them by the people of ſuch parts; and therefore there they are the more bound in all equitie to doe good.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> Touching his Maieſties Princely clemencie abuſed by ſuch as haue his Letters Patent,<note place="margin">Abuſe of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Letters Patents.</note> and goe vp and down with Briefes of them: as alſo for repreſſing of Rogues and Vagabonds, as much euerie where now ſwarming as if their were no Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and thereby robbing the Countries where they trauell, and be otherwiſe verie dangerous, and commit many euils, let it be only ſufficient by mentioning them to put you in mind of them, for ſome more ſeuere Law to be made to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them. Wracks alſo ſeeme verie hard, if not altogether vniuſt and vnrighteous, <hi>viz.</hi> that one ſhould be enriched with the loſſe &amp; vndoings of many: and that the principall owners ſhould not only loſe their Ships, with many mens liues for the moſt part, but alſo their goods. Theſe things conſidered, &amp; ſo amplified as by your wiſedomes they may be, what heart ſo flintie as not to be moued with compaſſion in that behalfe?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/> Touching the names of Puritans, Preſciſians, Schiſmaticks, &amp;c. diſgracefully caſt vpon ſuch as are ſound in all ſubſtantiall points of Chriſtian Doctrine, &amp; vnblameable in their life and conuerſation, &amp; not onely vpon ſuch Miniſters, but alſo vpon all other that doe moſt <hi>endeauour to keepe a good conſcience in all things towards God and men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note> how gracious a thing were it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this for the time to come? The rather becauſe many young Chriſtians are hereby much diſcouraged. Eſpecially it ſeemeth fit to reſtraine Preachers in Pulpits from all ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull and reproachfull ſpeeches. Alas it is too lamentable that many young ſtriplings, that had need to be confined to ſome places till their beards were growne, &amp; themſelues were men (as hauing been born Miniſters before their time) ſtarting vp into Pulpits, hauing no word of exhortation, neither any
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1764:40"/>ſound Doctrine to deliuer; It is (I ſay) lamentable, that ſuch ſhould euen in great Congregations ſpend the time in ſuch rayling, and yet by profane and ignorant men, be thought to preach excellently. I hope that if ſome of the moſt Reuerend Biſhops knew this abuſe, they would doe ſome thing for reformation hereof. But a Law in this behalfe were beſt of all.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> I had thought before to haue commended to your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian wiſedomes diuers caſes of Marriage.<note place="margin">Diuers caſes of marriage.</note> As that young men newly married ſhould not be ſuffered preſently to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell for two or three yeeres together: Againſt marriages alſo without conſent of Parents: at leaſt contrarie to the minds of religious Parents, that are able to ſhew good reaſons of their contrarie mindes: That all Licences for marriages without thriſe ſolemne asking (as they call it) ſhould be made vnlawfull: That the Wife being iuſtly diuorced for Adulterie, the innocent partie may haue libertie to marrie without contradiction; there being no heauier thing for ſtrong and luſtie men then to be reſtrained from marriage: And that the generall reſtraint of all perſons from marriage for almoſt halfe the yeere, ſhould be vtterly aboliſhed, the ſame being contrarie to the Word,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.3.</note> and a Doctrine of Deuils, and being altogether Papall, and hauing no vſe but to pay for Licences, and being oftentimes the cauſe of much car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall filthineſſe before marriage, and ſometime the man dying before marriage, and leauing his contracted Wife with childe, to her perpetuall infamie, and to the making of the childe ſo borne no better then a Baſtard. Some good reaſon may be giuen for celebration of marriages betwixt eight and twelue of the clocke in the forenoones: but certainly none can be giuen of the former: ſaue onely the Siluer benefit of Eccleſiaſticall Courts, and their Officers. But of theſe and ſome other marriage caſes, I dare not ſpeak more largely, hauing beene ſo ample before, though nothing ſo ample as I could haue beene.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:1764:40"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> The ſame reaſon is of my ſilence of diligent yeerely mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering of men,<note place="margin">Yeerely muſtering of men &amp;c.</note> for the better fitting of them for times of need: as alſo of good care of Furniture for Warre, without any iugling to make the Furniture of one to ſerue for many, the ſame alſo I ſay for my ſilence of the Eccleſiaſticall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and gouernment, the deſire whereof hath beene a greater cauſe of the reſtraint of Miniſters, then their not conforming. Herein I haue beene the more ſilent, becauſe the ſame hath heretofore and more lately beene amply, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, and ſubſtantially laid forth by other, wherein we alone differ from all other reformed Churches. And if it ſhall not pleaſe his Maieſtie generally to eſtabliſh it according to Gods Word; and other Churches throughout his Kingdome; yet if he might be perſwaded to tollerate it in ſome places, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the ſame by his owne Princely wiſedome, as I doubt not but that they which ſhall enioy the ſame, will beare all charges thereto belonging, without any preiudice to any other Miniſters, ſo I am perſwaded that vſe thereof would <hi>emittere</hi> ſuch a fragrant ſmell, as that all other would be the more in loue therewith: thereby alſo would be that ſweet peace, that is ſo often commended in the Scripture: Yea, I doubt not, but that his Maieſtie would better affect it, and the louers thereof, then euer he hath done. As the want of any member (though neuer ſo little) maketh the whole body the more impotent, ſo the want of the holy Diſcipline maketh the whole Miniſterie the weaker, and leſſe effectuall. If this little hereof ſpoken be offenciue to any, yet let it not (I humbly beceech you) hinder my former motions, or any of them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/> Againſt the abuſes of Excommunication and citing of men to Eccleſiaſticall Courts by Apparitors without any preſentment againſt perſons ſo cited, contrarie to our owne Canons: againſt proceeding alſo of ſuch Courts for bare abſence, vpon the bare word of an Apparitor that maketh
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1764:41"/>no conſcience of any thing: as alſo againſt ſo citing of men, and ſuch proceeding againſt them (euen ſometime, neuer at all cited) without regard of age, of the ſeaſon of the yeere, of diſtance of place, &amp;c. I hope that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome other will ſpeake, or this ſhort mention will be ſufficient: or it may be ſome other will reforme ſuch diſorders.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/> Laſt of all, becauſe abſence of the better ſort ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times doth ſtrengthen the worſe part,<note place="margin">Parliament men to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Ezek. 46.10.</hi>
               </note> as experience hath taught in the Vniuerſities, therefore as the Lord by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> commandeth that in his worſhip, <hi>The Prince and the people ſhould come together thereunto, and goe away together there-from,</hi> ſo may it pleaſe you all that <hi>wiſh well vnto Zion, and loue the peace of Ieruſalem</hi> to doe the like in this your ſeruice of God, of his Maieſtie, and of the whole Kingdome, at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Seſſion of the Parliament, and on euerie day for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Seſſion.<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> How highly did all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſinne (euen <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelfe) in the abſence of <hi>Moſes</hi> but a few dayes? How effectuall for Chriſt,<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.51.</note> was one weake word of <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> euen to the diſſoluing of the whole Councell of the Prieſts and Phariſees againſt Chriſt?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/> To ſhut vp all that I haue ſpoken by the priuiledge and libertie of Subiects,<note place="margin">The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</note> for crauing helpe of your moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court in the former Aduertiſements preſented vnto you, I doe humbly craue the gracious pardon of his moſt Excellent Maieſtie, of his Princely Sonne, and of you all of any thing wherein for matter or manner I haue erred, euen with the like words (ſome few onely changed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the difference of perſons to whom I ſpeake, and of the future Tenſe into the time paſt) euen with like words (I ſay) (except onely before excepted) doe I craue this pardon that <hi>Luther</hi> once vſed to the Emperour and other Princes before whom he pleaded his cauſe.<note place="margin">Sleidan, comment. lib. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Si quid à me peccatum fuerit potentiſſime Rex, illuſtriſſime Princeps,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1764:41"/>nobiliſſimi Marchiones atque Comites, honoratiſſimique Barones alijque huius Regni Proceres, vel verbis minimè proprijs, neque tanto conſeſſu dignis, vel etiam phraſibus parùm elegantibus atque decoris, totum hoc mihi peto condonari propter vitae genus, in quo aliquam (mihi obſecro liceat interponere maximam) aetatis par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem conſumpſi.</hi> For alas, I neither haue liued in the Court (at leaſt long together) for theſe fourtie yeeres and more, nor in the Citie, but in the Countrey, where I haue not beene acquainted with Court ſpeech, or otherwiſe exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed with Learning, as ſome haue beene. Neither (I doe moſt humbly beſeech you) let the concealing of my name be any preiudice to this my humble Petition. Becauſe I haue ſpoken ſomewhat againſt Papiſts I haue therefore concealed my name, leaſt being knowne I ſhould fall into ſome of their hands. For they are a bloodie brood, a <hi>generation of vipers,</hi> yea, <hi>a generation whoſe teeth are as ſwords,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 37. Pro. 30.14</note> 
               <hi>and their iawe teeth as kniues, to deuour the poore from the earth, and the needie from among men.</hi> The poore and needie? Yea alſo, the mightieſt Monarkes in the World. They eat their God and kill their Kings. And therefore as the Elders of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid among themſelues of <hi>Iehu,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 10 14.</note> 
               <hi>Behold two Kings could not ſtand before him, how then ſhall we ſtand?</hi> So ſay I of them, <hi>Behold they deuour their God</hi> (and ſo may moſt truly be called <hi>Bellygods</hi>) <hi>and they murther Princes;</hi> How then can ſuch a poore wretch as I am ſtand before them? The God of grace direct you all (Nobles, Knights, and Burgeſſes) by his Spirit of grace, ſo to goe to our moſt Noble and gracious King,<note place="margin">Neh. 1.4. and 2.1. &amp;c. Eſt. 4.16. &amp; 5.1. &amp;c.</note> as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did to <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> and <hi>Eſter</hi> vnto <hi>Ahaſhueroſh,</hi> that thereby ye may finde that grace with his moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Maieſtie, that <hi>Nehemiah</hi> found with <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Eſter</hi> with <hi>Ahaſhueroſh</hi> for her ſelfe and all the <hi>Iewes.</hi> And the ſame God ſhew me and all before ſupplicated for, ſuch fauour with his Maieſtie, and Princely
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1764:42"/>Sonne, and you all for our ſelues, and for the Houſe of God in this his Kingdome,<note place="margin">Ezra 7.27.</note> that we may ſay, as <hi>Ezra</hi> ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of our Fathers, which hath put ſuch a thing as this into the Kings heart, to beautifie the Houſe of the Lord here in England, and hath extended mercie vnto vs before the King and his councellors, and before all the kings mightie Princes. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 16.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Quit you like men: be ſtrong.</p>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:1764:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
